Class and object diagrams will keep us
busy this week and also at least next
week, as the first typical
and most prominent representatives of UML.
And we'll start this
week with class diagrams.
Here's just an example.
You don't need to be able
to read this right now, of course.
We'll explain the syntax for it later.
Here you can see some
details, which we will discuss later.
There are also some detail deviations from it,
as it will sometimes be in the lecture.
So the language is not fully formal,
that's why sometimes there are small deviations.
For example, we're going to illustrate exactly
the passage here a little bit differently.
When we make class diagrams ourselves,
we'll usually add types to the
attributes that show up here, etc.
There are various
specifics and small details.
But as a first impression, you can
just take a look at this class diagram.
So here are kind
of different classes represented.
Obviously, somehow a university
situation has been modeled.
Professor, institute, lecture, student.
There are classes.
It could somehow
be the participants occurring
in a system/program/model that
should be captured here.
Then there are
apparently some attributes that
the individual classes have, so that
objects of those classes (the professor,
concretely, or a concrete institute)
will have manifestations of those attributes.
And there are apparently some
relationships represented here as well.
There seem to be
different kinds of relations, too.
Sometimes there are numbers like this
on here, or some very special annotation.
We're going to do all of that.
So learning goals for this part
of the lecture here are that on
the one hand you
learn this modeling language.
That you can read something like this
and understand why things are annotated differently here.
And on the other hand, of course, to
learn to set up models yourself with it
(little by little, also via the exercise mode).
Okay, now what has to go into
such a class diagram, or what has to
happen first, before you start
to develop an object-oriented system?
What should be modeled before that?
In particular, model statically first.
Here are a couple of
questions that come up, and
the answers to them will
ultimately feed into the class diagram.
So first of all, obviously:
What objects or classes are needed?
So what are the entities?
In the example,
professor, institute, etc., which
occur in the scenario and
are therefore to be modeled.
Also:
How many classes are needed?
Will one have a class
for each thing that can occur?
Or is it just about the central
concepts from the domain that one is modeling?
What are the attributes of these classes
and what are the relationships between them?
So what should be written as attributes
to which classes, and how are they linked?
In the example just now, there
were somehow not pairwise relationships between
all classes via this link
here, but only for selected pairs.
This must come from somewhere,
must be modeled by something.
Which operations/methods do
these classes provide?
That didn't appear at all in the example.
Those were the empty boxes,
which stood below the classes.
Operations would have
to be recorded there.
This was not done in the example.
How do these methods work together?
That would be more
a question for dynamic modeling.
In which states can objects be?
This certainly has something
to do with attributes.
Which messages are sent
to other objects and when?
Which messages there are,
that would be static.
When exactly that happens would again
be a question for dynamic modeling,
which we can only answer later
and not with class and object diagrams.
Some of these points already
have appeal to dynamic modeling.
But already for this static modeling, if
you answer the first few questions
here, you have to get going somehow.
There are various approaches
to this in the literature.
They are not
completely formal or systematic.
For example, the first thing is
to somehow record requirements for a domain.
Requirements gathering.
The first step would
be to determine the classes.
Later, you can try to
establish relationships between the classes in
order to ultimately work
towards the class diagram.
What I would like to do now in
the next slides is to simply pick an example
from one of the books that
I presented at the beginning of
the lecture in the first week and
at least simulate this finding of classes.
This won't be
completely systematic, but at
least it gives you an
idea of how to proceed.
Even if you have such a task
in the exercises that you are given
a scenario and you are
supposed to identify the classes (and
later also the properties
and relationships between them).
We'll do that with the following example.
This is in English because, as I
said, it's taken from one of the books,
and that was the English language book.
We will discuss it a bit superficially
here, and we will not fill in
all the class diagram elements.
But you should get an impression
and you should be able to copy
it when you get such an exercise.
Let's assume that a library is
to be modeled in some way.
And in advance, some
use cases were recorded.
In other words, we wrote down what the system
to be designed is supposed to do in the end.
And one of these use cases would be
to register a new member in the library.
And that was written
down here in tabular form.
In each case, what a user
would like to do with the
system from an external black box perspective,
so to speak, what actions are executed.
And then it says in each case
how the system should react to that.
Here:
A customer fills out a form with name,
address and phone number, and
gives that to the employee.
The clerk, or the employee, asks
the system to create a new member.
The system responds by
asking for more information.
This information is entered.
The system reads the data
and creates a new member entry.
Gives it a
unique identification number, etc.
All this was written down verbally.
And now the first question
would be, in the design:
What would have to be the classes
that you want to hold on to?
What are somehow types of recurring objects
here, of objects to be captured together,
that play a role in
describing the state of the system?
Of course, that would be
just one of many use cases.
There would be others to add
new books, check out books, return a
book, perhaps remove books from the
catalog, create user account statements, etc.
What might one learn from this about the
possible classes one might want to capture here?
Well, a very naive approach
would be to simply look:
What terms are in here?
And the obvious approach would
be to look at nouns/nouns first.
Because classes are things.
Not verbs, but subjects
and objects of these sentences.
And that sounds very naive,
but it's actually a first
step you can take
to find candidates for classes.
And if we just do that here,
pick out all the nouns in this English
text, here are all of them in bold.
And that's quite a lot.
You certainly don't want to have that
many classes in the system in the end.
Not all of them
will actually become a class.
You can now take these terms
and filter or group them and
find out which of them
should actually be a class.
What you have to
record in your class diagram.
And there you can
first make some observations.
For example, it's noticeable that
there are certain entities here that
seem to form composite entities.
So for those it makes direct sense to
encapsulate them as a class that has different attributes.
This is the case for
members or customers, for example.
Because here it says something like this:
Customer has a name, an
address and a phone number.
These are apparently
attributes of this customer.
And customer is already such a
term, "the customer" is already very domain-specific.
You could also say more generally:
It's about a member.
If you look:
What are composite entities?
There are at least two, namely:
The member seems to be composite because
there is supposed to be an identification
number in the system
and certain other information.
And the system itself
also seems to be composite
because it contains,
for example, the members.
What were other nouns that occurred here?
Customer, I had already said,
is the same as a member.
You could look for synonyms and say:
Customer and Member are synonyms.
Only for one of them
you will have to introduce a
class, the other one will
just be another name for it.
What other nouns were there?
User.
But that's also just another synonym.
User, Customer, Member, all refers to
the same actors in the system.
So no new classes, but Customer and
User will also be the class Member later.
Application-Form, that is actually here
only a sheet of paper,
on which the customer enters
his data at the beginning.
So nothing that is
represented in the system itself.
The data later is.
But this application, this
form, which is filled
out, is nothing that
occurs in the system itself.
So you could say:
That's not an indication that it
has to be introduced as a class.
Then there is the request.
That was something that
the employee should trigger
(like by selecting a menu,
an entry in the system).
So like application form rather
not part of a data structure.
So nothing that needs
to be stored explicitly somehow.
Then there was the
customer name, address, phone number.
I had already motivated that earlier:
On the one hand, these are attributes of
Member, and on the other hand, they are
also indications that Member
should be a class.
We had talked about encapsulation.
So the composition of single entities always speaks
for the fact that they should be classes.
On the other hand, such single terms as the
name, which is not further decomposed apart from first and
last name, speak for the fact that
they are perhaps rather attributes of other classes.
And there must not necessarily be an own
class for the name or the phone number.
That is, these would be attributes that
we would assign (in the
class diagram) to the Member class.
The Clerk is of course an actor, but
has here only the role to serve the system.
He would not himself
be represented in the software.
Except perhaps:
The Clerk also needs to
be stored with his contact
information, perhaps to
manage the library's employees.
When it comes to the library
itself, the "business", borrowing books, etc., the
Clerk himself is not something
that needs to be stored.
What else is there?
Identification-Number is also
part of Member, so
would be an attribute of the Member
class, like those three terms at the end.
What else shows up there?
Data and Information, these are simply also
the things that are stored as members.
Data and Information were simply collective
terms for these attributes, not new classes.
Okay, that as such not a
complete recipe, but a certain intuitive
approach to first identify from free
text what can be classes and attributes.
The next step would be then to
derive between these classes, which one identified (the
system and the member term),
any relations, in order to
be able to hold in
the class diagram also relations.
To do that, we have to go
back to the text and look for descriptions
that somehow relate two classes, specifically member
and system, or somehow mention them together.
And when we do that, we find, for example,
the following sentence in the context of a larger point:
The system remembers
information about the member.
Information, that's the
attributes of Member.
And Member would be a class,
of which there are then different instances:
the concrete individual
members of the library.
How could we represent that, somehow a
relationship between the system and the members?
Let's call the system Library, so that we
don't call it just System in the abstract.
It's about the library.
So the system could be
a class, the library class.
And then there is the class Member.
There are already some attributes in
there that we indexed on
the pre-slide as properties of members.
And then there could be
a relationship between the two.
And there are already numbers written on
here that imply (and it will be formulated
later what exactly they mean), as a basic idea:
There is a library and it
has several members, "zero to star".
Where star means: any number of members.
Up to no members at all at the
beginning, when the library might be newly founded.
The library exists only once.
One could also ask whether this
must be a class or whether
it is sufficient to
have an object for it.
There is the notion of a singleton class.
Again, these are patterns that would
come into play in the advanced
programming techniques
lecture, for example.
But here, it's already conveyed a little
bit by the numbers and the information
about how many objects there
can be of the singleton classes.
In particular, how many
are in such a relationship.
The library manages
a collection of members,
and here it says how many that can be.
Of course, types would also
belong to the attributes here.
There we have here:
This is a number, this is an
address, here maybe just a string, etc.
That is not yet exactly
fixed on this level of the
class diagram, but would be also
task of the class diagram designer.
This is not very far yet, this picture.
Now one could add further use
cases, for example the creation of members.
Or in addition to the creation
of members, the creation of books.
The lending of books, etc.
This could lead to further
classes, but especially to further relationships.
Now here is simply shown, also
from the book, how after some consideration
of further such use cases
the picture might be refined.
For example, that in
addition to managing members, the
library also has a
collection of books to manage.
That's why there is a new class
Book, and then there are
also relationships between members and books.
For example, borrowing, that is, the
fact that a borrowing has taken place.
Or maybe that if a
book is not available, but
a member wants to borrow it,
you can then somehow create a reservation
that holds a reservation on that book.
So that when the book
becomes available, you can borrow it.
That would be a next
step in designing a class diagram.
And that's where you
can do further refinement.
So these relationships here,
they would just be strokes.
We're going to learn
that there are different types
of relationships that each
have their own meaning.
And if you analyze this here in
more detail, what nature these individual relationships
are, you could come to
the following picture, for example.
Where, on the one hand, one has
introduced more classes here, namely an explicit
membership catalog and a book catalog.
But above all, here the connections
have been refined, made more precise.
There are different types of symbols.
We'll look at all of that, what
that's supposed to mean in each case.
But the point is:
People have continued to refine the picture
here to ultimately get closer to implementation.
Each step adds information that is
motivated from the application domain, and
should later help with
the implementation of the system.
Here are different names for the connections
and also different ways of representing them.
Here, for example, it was decided
that what was here before as a
class for the borrowing
process is not strictly necessary.
Because you can also store the information
with the book or with the member.
While the reservation is something that should be
explicitly represented as a class, because there is
still external information necessary, for example
until when the book should remain reserved.
That as a first example
with not much detailed information yet,
but at least an impression how
such a class diagram should look like.
Okay, next we really
have to introduce syntax.
How exactly such a
class is to be notated.
There is a lot left vague here.
But I'll do that in another video.