Just as there are different ways
of entering the hierarchical or region states,
there are also different ways of exiting.
So we have to take
a look at that as well.
Let's look at a hierarchical state first,
and later at a regions state again.
In the hierarchical states there is
the exit from the composite state
as a whole.
This is, so to speak, the
counterpart to the standard entry, where you
just approach the overall state from the
outside and don't somehow pick out something inside.
And in the same way, here would be
the exit from the composite state as a whole,
without any further indication
as to which sub-state one would
like to leave the overall state from.
Then there is the possibility to
exit directly from a specific sub-state.
This corresponds or would be dual
to the explicit entry into a sub-state.
And then for entry, there were the two
variants: shallow and deep history.
There is nothing corresponding
to those on exit.
Yes, on exit, something may be
noted, in order to then, upon re-entry via history,
access information about where
we were last in this overall state.
But with the exit arrows themselves,
there are no additional variants for
history entry, history exit or so.
So for the hierarchical state, there are
just these two options.
And what do they mean in each case?
So, the exit from a
hierarchical state as a whole
simply means: as soon as the
trigger associated with the transition
(yes, there could be
a trigger on it here)
takes place, the overall state is simply exited.
No matter in which concrete
sub-state one is at the moment,
one simply leaves the overall state.
What about when you
exit from a specific sub-state?
Well then this transition, which probably
has a trigger on it, is
only selected if you are
actually currently
in the specific sub-state you
are supposed to exit from.
So in our example diagram, this would be
the state E, because this arrow goes out from E.
I.e., if there is
a trigger on it and that trigger occurs,
we can select this transition only
if we are actually currently in E.
If we are currently in C or
D, then we cannot trigger this exit.
Besides that, there are other possibilities:
an exit point as well as end states
or terminators over which we can also exit.
But these are not treated here.
So we will only
need these two exit possibilities.
What this means concretely for
an example would be something like this.
So, if we have a state
like this that is composite,
and we have one
exit from the overall state,
then in this case, that actually corresponds
to three arrows.
Namely, that we could have explicitly
exited from B, from C, and from D.
These three exits from specific
sub-states are replaced by a
single exit from the overall state.
Because then we don't have to say
where we are in the sub-state right now.
And this is exactly where we
save arrows in our wristwatch example,
because there we also have just such entries
and exits from or between overall states,
instead of having arrows for
every combination of sub-state and sub-state.
That's exactly the goal of
this kind of entry and
exit: to save
transitions in the representation.
And here, this very
example corresponds to that.
This would be when we don't have regions.
Now we still have to
look at what happens if
we have a region state
and we exit from that.
Then there is also the exit
from the composite state as a whole.
Then we would just leave,
no matter what sub-states we are
in right now in the regions.
There is the exit from
a sub-state, which is now
just located in one
of the possibly several regions.
And there is additionally
the exit through a join,
essentially a counterpart to
the entry through a fork.
Again, histories are not relevant
here on exit as a representation option.
Now, what do these exit
possibilities mean for regions states?
Well, if we want to exit
again from the state as a
whole, then this
is simply always possible.
Then, in each region,
the sub-state present there is simply exited.
So no matter in which sub-states
we are in the individual regions,
we can always choose
this exit from the whole.
What about exiting from a
specific sub-state?
Well, if we have something like this
situation, then we are only allowed to leave
the region state if we are actually
at the corresponding state in this region.
Yes, so we would be allowed to leave the regions state
altogether if we are here in B and here in C.
Or if we are here in B and here in D.
But not if we are here in
A and here in C or D.
So the composite state is left
only if one is
actually in the sub-state
in the corresponding region that this arrow exits from.
In the regions parallel to it,
one may be in any state.
So in this specific case, it is
like this: we would only be able to
exit if we are actually
in B in the first region.
That would be this case and this case.
And in this case, it's explicitly stated
which sub-state we should
be in per region.
And accordingly, the rule is as follows.
We can leave the
composite state via the join
exactly when we are in the
appropriately labeled state in each region.
So in the example we could exit only
when we are actually in B and D.
Not if we are in B and C or something.
If we are in B and C,
then we may exit over here,
and over here, but not over here.