We come to the next
property to be discussed in
Petri nets, namely
the concept of conflict.
This is again about two transitions,
which can be in conflict or not.
This is again relative
to a given marking.
So we need a Petri net with a given
marking, and then we can say
whether two transitions are in conflict.
And you can already see here,
in the definition, the word "concurrent" appears.
That is, this definition builds
on the concept of concurrency.
Two transitions are in conflict
if they are not activated
concurrently, but this is only because
they somehow get in each other's way.
So it can also be that
t and t' are not activated concurrently,
because one of the two
transitions itself is not activated.
Then it would not be a conflict.
So it is called a conflict
for two transitions t, t', if
they are both activated separately,
but they are not activated concurrently.
That is, each one could fire,
but they cannot both fire concurrently.
Because they are in conflict, or rather,
that is how a conflict is defined.
So exactly
this descriptive consideration.
This is then checked
with the pre-weight functions.
What is concurrent, we
have just discussed sufficiently.
And when a single transition is activated (i.e.
when you look at both of them individually),
we have also already discussed,
a few weeks ago even.
Okay, so how can there be a conflict?
The two transitions must have at least
one place in common in the precondition.
You can think that whenever we
have two transitions in conflict, there
must be a common
place in the precondition.
So there must be a place s such
that both the pre-weight function for t with
respect to s requires at least one
token and the pre-weight function for t'.
If this is not so, and
moreover t and t' are both
activated separately, then they
would also be activated concurrently.
However, this below does not mean
that one can take this as
the sole criterion to find conflicts.
It's just an indication of
a conflict again, so to speak.
So to suspect a conflict for
t and t' only makes sense if
they have at least one
common place in the preconditions.
It is not true that as soon
as there is such a common place in
the preconditions, there must
also be a conflict.
So, the presence of a conflict
must always be checked using the definition.
Okay, an example: a Petri
net with a certain marking.
Now one can ask which
transitions are in conflict here.
And this is a term again only for pairs.
There are only the
pairs (t1,t2), (t2,t3) and (t1,t3)
here for which it makes sense to wonder.
And already when we look at t1 and
t2, it turns out that they are in conflict.
And we also already see what
this can only be due to.
It can only be
because of this common place.
That is the only common place.
So somehow it could cause a conflict.
It doesn't have to, but it could.
For example, it wouldn't cause a
conflict if there were two tokens.
But as drawn here, there is a conflict.
And the check is simple using
the definition for activation and concurrency.
Yes, so t1 must be activated.
That is, the pre-weight function
for t1 (that would be this
one, because t1 requires exactly
one token each from s1 and
s2; those are the two arrows
here) is less-equal than the current marking.
The current marking has (1,1,1,1) on
s1 through s4 and then three zeros.
And this inequality here holds because at
each position there is a number on the
left that is no larger than on the right.
And that's the definition
of t1 being activated.
That showed up relatively early in
the lecture classes on Petri nets.
Very similarly, t2 is also activated.
Because there the
pre-weight function looks a
little bit different (because t2 requires a
token from s2 and s3 each), but also
this pre-weight function is
smaller-equal than the current marking.
On the other hand, t1
and t2 are not activated concurrently.
Because for this the sum of these two
pre-weight functions (here again written down as a sum)
would also have to be
smaller-equal than the current marking.
And this is just not the case.
Because although there are two and two,
that is four tokens, on the left
and four tokens on the
right, it does not fit position-wise.
So the sum here would
be (1,2,1) and then all zeros.
But (1,2,1) does
not fit here "underneath".
That means, t1 and t2
are actually not activated concurrently.
But they are individually activated,
and therefore they are in conflict.
We also know:
As soon as we would put another
token on here, both transitions would still be
activated individually and they would
also be activated simultaneously/parallel together.
That means, there would be
concurrency and just no conflict.
But as it is here, there
is the conflict between t1 and t2.
One can also consider that of
course t2 and t3 are in conflict.
Yes, there the picture is very similar, there
it's simply a matter of these three precondition places.
And then there's the problem here
that s3 only has one token, but
if we add the pre-weight functions of
t2 and t3, we would need a 2.
So t2 and t3 are also in
conflict, but t1 and t3 are not.
So, if we consider t1
and t3 as the relevant pair,
then we can do these sums here.
It says (1,1,0,0).
Here it says (0,0,1,1,0,0,0).
Yes, this then belongs here to t3,
this and this place are occupied.
Also this and this place
corresponds to a 1 in the
pre-weight, and then the sum would be
(1,1,1,1,0,0,0), and that would still fit under here.
That is, t1 and t3 are, after all,
activated concurrently, so they cannot be in conflict.
And also with the indication
from the previous slide, we know:
t1 and t3 can't be in conflict
anyway because they don't share a precondition place.
Yes, t1 depends only on these two
pre-condition places, t3 depends only on these.
There's no potential for conflict there.
Or you just do the math.
Okay, and this is again an observation
that we had already looked
at with causality and concurrency respectively.
With causality, we had noted
that that's a transitive term.
So if t1 is causal for t2, and t2 is
causal for t3, then t1 is also causal for t3.
With concurrency, we had
seen, this is not the case.
And this is also not
the case with the conflict relation.
So, it can be: t1 and t2 are in conflict,
t2 and t3 are in conflict,
but t1 and t3 are not.
That's exactly what we see here.
Okay, and that's all I've prepared
on conflict in examples here now.
Because the examples would be
very similar to the concurrency examples,
but just turned around in each case
so that there is just no concurrency.
So as soon as we have two
transitions, which are each activated.
Otherwise it's boring.
They must be each activated.
But they are not concurrent,
so they are automatically in conflict.
More on this in the exercise sessions, of course.