In the previous video I had spoken towards
the end of the non-determinism with Petri nets.
Especially in the execution, i.e. that
there can be several activated transitions for
a marking, which can then
also lead to different subsequent markings.
And I had already mentioned that
this results in a graph which
ultimately corresponds to
a flat state diagram.
And that is the flat state
diagram of exactly this Petri net.
That is now defined here on this slide.
I'll talk through that briefly and
then we'll see it on an example.
And it will be practiced, of course.
So, given a Petri net.
We know how this is mathematically given by
these five components: place set, transition set, pre-weight
functions, post-weight
functions, start marking.
And then we assign a flat
state diagram to this Petri net.
This always consists
of certain components
as defined mathematically earlier (where
we looked at graphs in general).
So there is the node set.
This is often called V for "vertices".
Or we can call it Z
for states, because of the state diagram.
And for that, we choose the
set of all markings reachable from m0.
Using exactly the reachability
notion that was defined here.
So any marking m that is
reachable in this way by a
finite sequence of transitions from m0
is packed into this set Z.
Reminder:
A Petri net
configuration, i.e. an assignment
of places of the Petri net with
tokens, corresponds to a state of the system.
Therefore it makes sense to choose exactly
that as the states in the state diagram.
Of course only the reachable markings.
Not all conceivable markings.
Because markings, which are not reachable
from the start marking, contribute nothing
to the understanding of the Petri net.
They can never be realized anyway.
Okay, then there is
the set of edge labels.
In a flat state diagram, after all,
we could label the edges between the nodes.
And for that here we
choose the set of transitions.
So on each edge between nodes
we will write a transition, namely
the transition that
led to this transition.
Which was activated
in the original marking
before the transition, and led
exactly to the subsequent state.
Then we get as edge set, or
transitions, exactly the triples consisting of marking,
transition, subsequent marking, for
which this relationship holds.
So we don't just
link any markings together.
But we have a transition from
m to m' with the label
t, so with label t at the
arrow, exactly when t is activated in
marking m, and after firing
exactly the marking m' arises.
Thus we have all
nodes, all edges, their labels.
As a rule, in a flat
state diagram, we still designate a
special state, namely the start state.
And here, logically, this
is the initial marking.
This is one of
these reachable markings, because
it is reachable after
the empty transition sequence.
So it fits, is an
element of the relevant state set.
Okay, so that's our flat state
diagram for our given Petri net.
And this is also
called the reachability graph.
It's a graph that represents
all the reachable markings, and
of course makes it clear
via the labels on the
edges how a particular
marking can be reached.
So in the end the firing
sequence can be traced in the graph.
This can become an infinite graph.
The Petri net is always finite.
The set S was finite,
the set T was finite, but
the reachability graph could
well be an infinite graph.
While every firing sequence is finite, there
may be an infinite number of them.
We're not going to consider
that here at the moment.
So here at the moment we will only
see an example of a finite reachability graph.
But we'll also come back to
at least one example of infinity later.
There the definition is unchanged, the
development is in principle also the
same, only of course you can't
paint an infinite graph on a slide
in finite time, as I'm about to
do now here for the example in sequence.
And that is, let's look at
exactly the reachability graph for this
Petri net, which we've
now seen several times.
That was our example Petri net
on the slides for the connection
between graphical
and mathematical representation.
And it was also the example that
I had used in an earlier video this
week for illustrating the mathematical
formulation of firing and reachability.
It helps, of course, to have
already done that for this example.
Because then we already know part of
the reachability graph directly now.
So, what will this
graph look like for this?
It will be on the next slide.
But I would like to
talk through the first few states,
so to speak, and then
just leave the graph to you.
So that you can look for or check
the rest of the transitions in there yourself.
So, by definition, this is a
graph that contains all all reachable
markings, especially, of course,
at least the initial marking.
And in fact, when we
set up such a reachability graph,
we start with the
initial marking, of course.
Because we already know that it
has to be present in the graph.
So, what is the start marking here?
Of course, we first have to agree on
how we want to write down the markings.
I had once said:
We like to use
tuples, in this case triples.
For this we have to decide in
which order we want to use the places.
And if they are called s1, s2, s3,
it is obvious to write
them down in this order.
So, the start marking as
a triple would be (1,2,0),
because these are the tokens on
the three places in the start state.
So that would explain this
part from this solution here.
You take (1,2,0) as the
first marking and also mark it
with this input
arrow as the start marking.
And then you have to
find more nodes, all reachable markings.
That means, you have to ask now, starting
from this start marking, which
is already in the graph:
What are the reachable markings?
And for this one must
look, which of the given transitions,
which exist in the Petri net, are
then fireable in the marking just present?
At the beginning, this
is the start marking.
That is, we simply have to consider:
What is fireable in this situation?
And in fact, only t1 is fireable.
And we already know
what comes out of that.
For one thing, we can check it.
Then there would be
two tokens down here afterwards.
So (0,1,2) would be the
next marking, after firing t1.
But we already know that,
because we have recalculated it here.
That was exactly the point:
From the start marking (1,2,0) we can
get this next marking by firing with t1.
So it is reachable, and therefore it
has to appear in the reachability graph.
And this would be exactly
the extension to this part.
So we would build up
the graph piece by piece now.
We started with (1,2,0) and we know:
After firing t1 we end up at (0,1,2).
There would be no
further arrows for the time
being, because no other transitions
are activated in the start marking.
Then we would look next:
Well, if there are
no more transitions from
it, what about this new marking (0,1,2)?
Are there any transitions from it?
For this we would have to
think of this token here set differently.
Now it is no
longer about the start marking,
but about the current marking (0,1,2).
So, if nothing lies here, one
token lies here, and here two,
which transition would be fireable then?
The t1 would not be fireable,
because of the imaginary zero here.
But t2 and t3 would both be
fireable, because they depend only on tokens in
s3, where now two would lie.
So we would know, next
t2 and t3 would be fireable.
And of course, we
also saw exactly that earlier.
Namely, in this example we had also
considered exactly from the marking m1, which is
present after firing t1, and finally
calculated that t2 and t3 are fireable,
and that thereby the two
markings (1,1,1) and (0,2,1) arise.
We can now plot this
on our graph in progress.
So we would extend the
piece we already had now.
On the one hand by
(with transition t2) the node (1,1,1),
and on the other hand by
(per transition t3) the subsequent marking (0,2,1).
So then we would have developed
this part of the graph, so to
speak, still without the arrows
going in the opposite direction.
So these four states and the initial marking
arrow, plus these three arrows here.
Then we would also know that we're not
going to have any more transitions from this node.
Because t2 and t3 are
activated and that's just about it.
So next we would look at
the two new states and think
about what is fireable from these.
But I don't have that
now already on existing slides.
So I didn't have any
more things calculated through here.
But of course you can do
the same considerations for the new markings.
Or take the Petri
net, think away these markings,
instead for example consider the situation, where
on each place exactly one token lies.
In order to consider how
it could go on from here.
So, what would happen if there were
exactly one token here, here and here?
Which transitions would
be activated then?
All of them!
Transition t1 because
of these two inputs.
Transition t2 because of this input.
Transition t3 because of this input.
So because of the presence of
a token on each relevant input.
That means, from the marking
(1,1,1) all three transitions are fireable.
This would lead to the fact that we
must actually have three outgoing arrows from (1,1,1).
And if we then calculate in
each case what comes out as a
subsequent marking, we find out, for example, that
if we execute t1, we come to (0,0,3).
So this state is added.
But we also notice:
If we fire t3 from (1,1,1), then
we would come to the
marking (1,2 0), which already exists.
Of course, we then do not
make a new node here with (1,2,0).
After all, we have a graph.
That is, we simply have a
back arrow labeled t3 in that case.
And it turns out that we
can still get here with t2.
Okay, and so we extend
the graph piece by piece.
For each new state we always
check which further transitions
are fireable from there.
If this leads to new nodes, we add them.
And for those we have to check again,
which further transitions are
possible starting from there.
If, on the other hand, we have
a backward arrow (like the one from
here to here), we don't have to look
again to see what is possible from this marking.
We already have this, so
all transitions starting from here
we have already looked at.
For example, that was just t1.
That doesn't change when we have
the connection between these two nodes.
Yeah, so it doesn't change
what would be possible from here.
And then we keep doing that until
at some point no new states are added.
This case does not
necessarily have to occur.
It can just be, if the reachability graph
is infinite, that this goes on and on.
That we always find new states.
But for this concrete Petri net with the
connections given here and
this starting marking it
results that after finitely many
steps no more markings are added.
And new transitions cannot be added either,
if we have considered all of them.
That is, then that
would be the result graph.
So that's then the reachability graph
for the Petri net given here.
And this is useful, because
it describes the overall behavior
of the Petri net in this form.
This is perhaps not as informative,
from a modeling point of view,
as this representation here, where we tell from the transitions,
so to speak, what they depend on.
That can be read
out here at most indirectly.
You would have to look at all t1
arrows to find out under
which conditions t1 is fireable.
But properties of the Petri net
can be examined in this representation.
In the first lecture on Petri
nets we had asked such questions:
How can the system reach a dead end?
And this can't be seen here directly,
whether after some firings it can happen
that no further transitions are possible.
However, in this accessibility
graph it is factually obvious.
We just have to see if there is a
node from which there are
no outgoing arrows, like this one.
And then we know:
Yes, indeed, this Petri net
can reach a dead end.
The system described by this
can develop in such a
way that at some point
no further transitions are possible.
For example, after t1, t3,
t3 we come to a situation
where no further steps are possible.
So then we can study properties of
the Petri net on this reachability graph.
This is true for dead ends.
This is true
for certain liveness questions.
The question about dead ends
is ultimately also the question:
Can the system always live on?
So we could investigate, for example:
Are there infinite processes here?
So is it possible for the
system to go on and on?
Yes.
It can reach an impasse, but if
it behaves favorably, if one makes sensible
choices, so to speak, as an
external agent (the Petri net itself
does not specify any
sequence or deterministic choice of
transitions), there are sequences of
this Petri net that are infinite.
If one avoids the dead
ends, the system can live infinitely.
And also questions about concurrencies, for example, can
be considered later on the basis of this structure.
Up to now, we
had only considered this informally.
Or questions about capacities.
One of the questions was:
Are there any resource upper limits?
That, for example, if you
consider the tokens as resources,
there are capacity restrictions.
And that is indeed what we see here.
So here we could not
have said immediately whether the
total number of tokens in
the system is somehow limited.
You would have had to think about
what the transitions do to the total
number of tokens or to the
number of tokens on individual places.
On the other hand, if we have this
graph, we can look at it and say:
There is never a
number greater than three.
That is, we know that
actually in each run of this
Petri net there are never more
than three tokens on any one place.
We can look at the graph and see that
when we've built it completely and, of course, correctly.
Okay, and this kind
of use of reachability graphs
will be our topic in
the next lecture, not today.
That will be the topic
of the next video or videos.