Coming to the end of the Petri net
chapter, I would like to talk
through one or two examples with you.
These are examples which once
again illustrate typical
scenarios or modeling patterns.
By "modeling patterns" I don't
mean anything formal like the
formally defined properties we have seen.
But simply certain approaches, how
one can handle typical situations
in dynamic systems
with Petri net modeling.
Some of this we've already seen.
In particular, this short video is
going to be about mutual exclusion.
And you've basically already seen that in the water gate example
in the practice exercises (actually, this will happen on the ninth sheet).
There were also some modeling
patterns in the afternoon example.
What I had discussed in the lecture and had
developed in the pipe tool as a Petri net.
For example, sources and
sinks were used: Transitions that
have no pre- or post-weight places.
Or we saw self-loops with a specific purpose,
namely to guard
certain places or transitions.
So, guard places, with which you can make
sure that certain transitions are
only fireable under certain conditions.
You could just look back at that example.
Or, for example, the capacity
bounds, that is, attempts to express
with Petri nets that certain places must not
contain more than a certain number of tokens.
Not because the Petri net
is bounded as a formal
property, but because it is
already brought in during modeling that
certain places must not contain more
than a certain number of tokens.
This is per se not given
when creating the Petri net, such restrictions.
This last aspect, constraining
capacity or the ability to
specify bounds, we're not going
to look at in this video.
This will be about mutual exclusion.
In that sense, this is the second
to last video of the Petri net chapter.
The other will then be the
last video of the Petri net chapter.
Let's first deal with the
concept of mutual exclusion, in
English "mutual exclusion", therefore called mutex
(the place we use for it).
The scenario here is
as follows, and this could
be very generally
applicable in various situations.
We somehow consider at least two
actors (in this case exactly two
actors), each having a critical region.
This somehow means an execution region,
an action region, which they
each want to enter exclusively.
In this sense, it is
"critical" because
not both actors should be in
the critical region at the same time.
So it must be prevented that the actors
enter their respective regions at the same time.
Because they could obstruct
each other there or
an undesirable behavior
could be the consequence.
So let's imagine that the two actors
are programs working on the hard disk.
The critical region could be writing to
a certain file, and we don't want both
actors to try to write to
the same file at the same time.
Therefore, there should always be at
most one actor in this critical region.
How can we think of
this as a Petri net design?
We might have two Petri nets,
for one actor and for the other.
I have stylized the system quite simply:
We simply imagine one
actor represented by this Petri
net and the second actor
represented by this Petri net.
In reality, there could be
larger Petri nets behind each.
So it could be that what is here
only one place, is in reality a whole
Petri net, in which something goes in, something
comes out (and what happens in here doesn't matter).
It doesn't have to be exactly one place.
That would be the non-critical region.
So somehow a Petri
net part, where any actions
can be executed, which have nothing
to do with the critical region.
The same is true for actor 2.
So that's non-critical region
1 and non-critical region
2 for the two actors.
And then there's also a
critical region for each actor, and
let that be K1, K2 for those two actors.
And the idea is to prevent both actors from
being in this region at the same time.
So it should be prevented that
at the same time, for example, a
token is here and a token is here.
Because that would mean that both actor 1
and actor 2 are in their critical region.
So if we consider these actions k1, k2,
nk1, nk2 as "actor 1 enters its critical
region", "actor 2 enters its
critical region" and analogously for
leaving the critical region and
entering the non-critical region, then certain
sequences of actions should not be
possible for the common overall system.
So it should not be possible: k1, k2,
i.e. actor 1 enters the critical region, and before
actor 1 has left the critical region,
actor 2 also enters its critical region.
Because if that then meant
that both actors were trying
to write to a file, they could
accidentally do so at the same time.
And of course the water gate example
from the exercise is quite similar.
That is about ships that are not supposed to be
in a certain part of the water gate at the same time.
That ultimately has to do
with critical region as well.
How could this be solved?
The Petri net, as stylized here,
of course has the property that it
would be quite possible to execute k1
and k2 directly one after the other.
Can we prevent this?
One can use a kind of guard place.
That is, an additional place which itself has no
functionality in the sense of actors 1 and 2.
But it ensures that certain
undesired behavior does not occur.
It is possible to synchronize via an
extra place, which is called a mutex place.
This is an auxiliary place, which is
often called mutex because of "mutual exclusion".
And what is the procedure here?
This is a place with
a token at the beginning.
And this token is always needed
when one of the two
actors enters its critical region.
So, for example, if actor 1
wants to enter his critical region, then,
of course, somehow the
non-critical region has to be
left, but in addition, this mutex
place has to be occupied with a
token, which actor 1 then consumes
in order to enter his critical region.
That is, to enter the
critical region (i.e., to bring the
token from here to here),
this token must additionally be consumed.
Which also means that then, for
example, directly afterwards the second actor
cannot enter its critical region.
Because that would mean executing k2, but
that also depends on this mutex place.
Let's assume that k1 fires.
Then this and this token
would disappear, here would be a
token, actor 1 would work
through his critical region and would
not release the token for the
mutex until the critical region is left.
So when actor 1 crosses
back over into the non-critical region,
that is, leaves its critical region.
Then this token would be returned and
could be reused by k1 or by k2.
Intuitively, this synchronization across this
common place ensures that both
actors cannot be in the
critical region at the same time.
This is, of course, based on
the fact that there is a conflict.
The respective transitions k1 and
k2 here are both activated in
the situation shown, but
just not activated concurrently.
But we have a conflict
exactly over this place here.
This prevents them both
from entering their critical region.
That would be the
informal and intuitive reasoning.
Of course, you can look
at this again formally by
just inspecting the reachability graph.
We want to show that there is never a
token in places K1 and K2 at the same time.
How can we show this?
We can plot the reachability graph.
I just did that without
developing that step by step.
So we see here, if
we take the place order NK1,
K1, K2, NK2 (so basically the way the
places were plotted here from left to right),
then we know
the start marking is (1,0,1,0,1).
We can see that here.
And then, in each case, it is
drawn which transitions are executable and what
the markings reached by them look like.
We can actually see here, for one thing, that
there are no sequences of the kind k1, k2.
If k1 was executed, then before
k2 can be executed, nk1 must
be executed at least once more.
That is one observation.
And the other observation is indeed
that among all the reachable markings,
there is none where both
K1 and K2 contain a 1.
Here, respectively, the two interesting places
K1, K2 are marked in bold.
And there is simply no reachable marking where
there is a 1 here and here respectively.
The mutex place has
successfully achieved that here.
That would be the
simplest example for mutual exclusion.
And as I said, it shows up
in many examples and applications of Petri nets.
One might also ask:
Where would this have
helped us in the past?
And well, actually also in the example
before in the context of the Dining
Philosophers one can make
use of mutual exclusion.
At least one can see this very
easily if one simplifies the
problem and considers only two philosophers.
In general, one could also
look for solutions for larger constellations
of dining philosophers,
following such synchronization ideas.
I discuss this now
only for the simplest case.
We look at the Dining Philosophers.
We just did that recently, so
I don't need to discuss that further.
We'll look at the simplification
that we sent one
of the three philosophers home.
So there are only
two dining philosophers left.
We see that down here as well.
So philosopher 3 is
gone and it's one less
fork (otherwise the problem
wouldn't be as interesting).
But we now have P1,
P2 and the intervening F1, F2.
Now you could have them sit down
a little differently, facing each other, etc.
But that doesn't change the problem.
The problem is that
there are still deadlocks
in the simplified Petri net.
That is, even here it can happen that
P1, P2 starve because they
behave in an unfavorable way.
By both grabbing the right fork and
then not being able to eat, nor
being able to put the forks back because
they have to grab the left fork first.
Also here in this Petri
net a deadlock is still possible.
So maybe synchronization
could help us there.
So we can try to introduce an extra mutex
place that somehow prevents, for example,
P1 and P2 from both grabbing exactly
one fork and then not being
able to get the second fork.
Maybe with a twist,
you can actually solve the
problem here at the application level, so
to speak, without an extra mutex place.
Namely if one makes
the mental leap to say:
How would it be, then, if
the two philosophers changed their behavior slightly?
Namely, one could make one of
them a left-handed person, that is,
prescribe a change of handedness.
What would that look like?
Here I made P1
a left-handed person right away.
That is, P1's behavior would no longer be
to grab the right fork first
and then wait for the left.
But to grab the left fork first
and then wait for the right one.
This is expressed here in the
Petri net by simply bending two arrows.
In each case the arrows, where philosopher
1 accesses the forks 1 and 2.
They were bent exactly in such a
way that the arrow, which led before
from F2 to something at the philosopher 1,
now instead comes from where F1 was before.
So exactly these two
arrows now run crosswise.
Now I claim that this solves the problem.
Why?
This leads to the fact that now
not both reach first for the right fork,
but P1 for the left and P2 for the right.
That is, this fork F1 would now be
the one grabbed first for both of them.
And that ultimately makes it
a synchronization point or mutex place.
How can we convince ourselves of this?
We could diagram the Petri net again in
a different way to make it more obvious.
Now this is a little asymmetrical
because I removed the third philosopher.
We can represent exactly
the same Petri net by
shaking it a bit
and rearranging the nodes.
Now, you'll either have to believe me or
compare it on the slides side by side,
that this is the same Petri
net as this one (just painted differently).
So exactly the same connections.
And here it becomes now more obvious
that the F1-place acts like a mutex.
This Petri net, as it is
shown here, is free of deadlock.
You can take my word for that, or
play it out, or plot the reachability graph.
The point is that here both P1 and P2,
to be filled, must each
fire this or that transition.
And they both access F1.
That is, if, for example, philosopher 1
reaches for his left fork (for F1),
then this very token
would disappear up here.
And then philosopher 2 is practically
paralyzed and can only become active again
when philosopher 1 has put down
this fork again, i.e. has eaten.
This is a conflict of course.
That is, these two transitions are in
conflict with respect to the fork F1.
This was just not the
case in the original philosopher problem.
There, at the beginning, the actions
of reaching for the right fork were
concurrent for all three philosophers.
Which sounds nice at
first, since it is parallel.
But that led to a deadlock,
while here by this introduction of the
conflict, the mutual exclusion,
this mutex-place, it is finally
ensured that not simply both philosophers
reach wildly for the first fork.
But only one of them can do that,
and afterwards the other one cannot do anything immediately.
But when philosopher 1 has finished eating,
philosopher 2 can take his turn again.
That is, here we
prevent deadlock by synchronization, by
using this mutex place ultimately.
This is a very typical
modeling pattern in various applications.