Let's go back to our wristwatch example.
As a reminder, it looks like this so far.
The hour and minute counts
are implemented in parallel regions.
We had used a broadcast effect so that when
the minute counter here jumps from 59 to 0,
it triggers an hour effect that
causes the hour count to advance here.
We had used an effect to say that
whenever the minute counter goes to
zero, there should be a beep.
We have the alarm on and off
setting, and we have these transitions between these
two composite states to get from
the time display to the alarm setting
and back, and to change between
on and off in the alarm setting.
Are we done?
No, there are still problems.
Namely, one major problem is that
when we return to the time display
from the alarm setting,
it always jumps to zero.
Why is that?
We had last discussed
what the consequences of
these entry/exit options are.
And for example, here's how it works:
Suppose we are at 2:58,
so we have state 2 in the hour
count and state 58 in the minute count.
Then button 'a' is pressed,
so this trigger is fired.
What does it do?
We had said we leave the
overall state, that is, we leave both
regions, we end up here in the
alarm state, initially at
the on sub-state, because that's the start state;
then maybe we turn the alarm on and
off several times (that's where we would use
'b' to switch back and forth between these
two sub-states), then we press 'a'
again, so we fire trigger 'a'.
What would that do?
We would leave that sub-state, go
back to that more complex regions
state, and we would do
that with the default entry.
And that means that in each
region, we would choose the initial state.
Then we end up back at
zero and zero, instead of 2:58.
That's not intentional, of course, and
that's also true the other way around.
So whatever was going on last in the
alarm setting, so to speak, is ignored when
we switch to the time display and back.
What makes this clear?
Suppose we have a time, we switch with 'a'
to the alarm setting, then that is first On,
then we press 'b', are Off, then we press
button 'a', then we get back into this regions state,
switch there maybe a few times,
press button 'a' again at some point.
What happens then?
We leave that right state,
get into the left state, use
the default entry there, and that says
we start back at the
start state of that hierarchical state.
So we're back at On, even though the
last time we were
in this left state,
we chose the sub-state Off.
So these transitions in this
way (as used before) forget what
was in each of the sub-states.
This is not surprising because
we are not using the history,
which was actually introduced precisely for
the purpose of not forgetting such sub-states.
In this example, we have so far
only used the exit from the
overall state and the
default entry into composite states.
And that just doesn't exhaust the possibilities
we have for not forgetting sub-states (i.e., the
last state in a hierarchical
state or a regions state).
So, the problems were to be expected
because we haven't used history nodes yet.
And the solution, of course, is
to actually use entries via history.
In fact, in this
specific example, it doesn't
even matter if we
use shallow or deep history.
Why?
Well, because there are no
deeper nesting levels here at all.
So both the right regions state
and the left hierarchical state have
exactly one more nesting level
and no deeper hierarchical nestings
where it would make a difference
whether we use deep or shallow history.
I'll use the shallow
history here in a moment.
Since we have two regions to enter
when we transition to the right
regions state, we actually need two history
states, one in each of the two regions.
And the entry transition is
then realized via a fork.
So here, from right to left, we
can say we're introducing a shallow
history, and for this 'a' transition,
we just go to the history node here.
When we go from left to right,
we want to enter these
two regions, and in both
regions we want to use the fact
that we could remember what the
last hour or minute state was.
Because the 'a' transition to the right
uses a fork to enter the history nodes
in the two regions.
And that then looks like this.
Not much has changed in the substates.
For example, this region is as before,
and so is this one.
These history nodes have been added.
Shallow history, because there
is no asterisk on it.
The entry to the right happens via
this fork, which then points to the
two history nodes, and from right to
left we also go via a history node.
If we compare this picture
with this diagram, we can see
exactly where the differences are. So the two
right and left overall states have
not changed significantly, but
the transitions are now more precisely
designed and ensure that
we remember the sub-states.
Now, if we were at 2:58 in the time display,
we would then
switch to the alarm setting state with
'a'. The first time, we will go to On
because the history node has this arrow pointing to
On. Then we can switch back and forth with 'b'
several times or not, and would then go back
to the regions state on the right with 'a',
but we would not do that via the default entry,
but rather use these
history nodes via this fork. And then it would be the case
that when we return, we don't go to zero
here, because we've been in this region,
this overall state before, namely at 2:58.
That is, these two history nodes would
ensure that, when we return to
this right complex state, we would be
at 2:58 and not at 0:00.
And vice versa, if we switched here
to Off, then returned here with 'a'
to the hour and minute display
and then pressed 'a' again.
Then we would not land at On,
but wherever we were last in the left
hierarchical state. And if
that was Off, then we would also land at Off.
This means these two problems mentioned here
would be solved exactly by this.
As mentioned, on the one hand, we could have
also used deep history in each case,
because there is no deeper nesting
at all.
On the other hand, we
would not have needed to
draw the arrows that
start from history nodes.
These three arrows are only used if we have
never been in the respective state in the respective
region or nesting level; if such
a history node has no direct outgoing
arrow, then the corresponding
start node from the respective region or nesting
level is simply taken. And since it is
the case here that
the history nodes always
point to the sub-state anyway,
which is also indicated by the
start state in the corresponding place,
omitting these three
arrows would make no difference.
We need such arrows especially when, on first entering a
state via a history node, we want to go
to a different state than what the
start state of that level would
be if we came via
default entry rather than history.
So, those are a couple of variations:
we could have omitted those
three arrows, and we could have
used deep history instead of shallow history.
So are we done, now that we have
gone from that case to this diagram?
No, there's still something missing.
What is still missing?
Well, what hasn't been implemented yet is
that this alarm setting really has something
to do with whether or not there is
a beep on the transition to a full hour.
Here there is this effect: when
we jump to the 0th minute,
that is, to a full hour,
then a signal is triggered here.
Actually, the clock should only trigger the
signal when the alarm is actually set,
but so far there is no connection or
communication between the fact that the
alarm is on or off, and
the fact of whether it beeps here or not.
So we have to transport some more
information and we can
do that via a flag.
This is like a
variable in a programming language,
a variable in which we can
store values, for example a Boolean variable,
which we can switch on and
off, true and false, zero and one.
We will call this AL for
alarm and use it to get this
beep effect, this signal tone, under control.
This means, on the one hand, that when triggering
this beep, we should take into account
whether the alarm is on or not,
and thus check this flag to see
if it is on or off.
On the other hand, of course, we
have to make sure that it's also set
to on and off at some point,
that is, during these transitions between these
states here in the alarm setting, we
should do something with this alarm flag.
We'll see how that happens in a
moment and what that looks like, but
the basic idea is: we use this alarm flag,
and use it when the signal tone is triggered
to check whether that should happen, and
manipulate it when turning the alarm on and off.
Furthermore, by means of this alarm flag, we
will actually also avoid using the shallow history
in the alarm setting
sub-state, in the left part.
So if we're going to introduce a flag anyway that
tells us whether the alarm is on or off, then
we don't need this history node at
all, because upon entry here we can just as easily
read from this flag
whether we want to go to this state or that state.
What does that look like then?
With that, we move on to this diagram.
We can compare that again
with what we have so far.
What changes there?
So again, the main parts: the
regions don't change, nor does this inner
structure of this left hierarchical
state, but especially here at
the transitions we do something: namely,
instead of using the history to go from right
to left, we simply make it dependent on this flag
whether we go to the On or the Off state.
We're allowed to do that by
adding a condition to this trigger.
If you look at the previous slides, you
can see that this is a possible description,
that we have a trigger and another possible
condition, and that would be this query
of this alarm flag again.
That has to be set somewhere.
That's what's happening here.
When switching between two sub-states,
we may also trigger an effect.
Such an effect can be
to toggle this alarm flag.
So if we switch to Off with the
'b' button, we set Alarm to zero and
if we switch to On, we set Alarm to one.
We take advantage of that when we enter
this left setting state by making that dependent
on the alarm flag, whether we want to go
this way or that way and very importantly of course:
We also use the alarm flag here
to trigger that beep, that signal, only
when we enter the zero state and
the alarm flag is currently set to one.
Those are the differences between
this diagram and that one.
Is that it then?
Well, we still need to somehow determine how
the alarm flag is set at the beginning.
At some point in the
beginning, this overall diagram is entered.
We know we start in the hour-minute
display because the start node points to it here.
We choose the default entry for this, which
is the start state for hour-minute 0:00,
but is the alarm flag set or not?
That still needs to be clarified.
We will do that in a moment
and in the course of that we will
also model the third aspect,
namely that the clock has
a battery that can run out, and when
the battery runs out, you should replace it.
In doing so, however, the hours and
minutes should be reset to zero.
The clock then starts running again
at zero and the alarm flag,
i.e., the alarm, should always
be on at the beginning.
This is the place where we also set
whether the alarm is originally on or not.
So we're modeling that the clock
has a battery that can run out,
needs to be changed, and in that
case something happens to the state.
Namely, we want that if the battery was
empty, we don't, for example, enter
the states via the
history, but rather start at 0:00. That's one aspect.
The other aspect:
We want the alarm flag to be set
to one. That is, when you put a new battery
in the clock, and also at the very
beginning, the alarm state is simply always one.
And this could be achieved as follows:
We take everything that
we have so far in the state diagram,
which was this part, and we wrap that
again in a hierarchical state,
namely how the clock
behaves when the battery is not empty.
Everything here is developed exactly as
before. And then, not in parallel to that,
but independent of it, we have another
state that is for when the
battery is empty. And when the watch
is delivered, the battery compartment is empty
and the battery is empty. That is
the very beginning of the entire process.
When a battery is inserted, on the one
hand we enter this part here, and we know
that we then start at this
start state, so we enter via the
default entry here at zero and zero, and we
set the alarm flag to one in the process.
Then what happens is whatever
the previous behavior was,
time progresses, we can change
the alarm setting, we can
turn it on and off, so that
it beeps only when the alarm is on.
When we switch back to
the alarm setting, the flag is
used to check whether the alarm
is on or not, etc.
Then at some point, of course, the battery can run out.
This causes us to end
up in this state again:
Battery is empty.
We can only leave this
state by inserting a new battery.
What happens in the process?
Then we end up at 0:00 again, as
we would expect after losing the
battery and inserting a new one.
We end up at 0:00 because we
don't use the history node, but rather
the default entry,
the two sub-start states
0 and 0. And we also always set the alarm
flag to one when we insert a battery, which means
that if we then pressed 'a' for the first
time, we would always end up in that sub-state.
And that's supposed to be our
final modeling for this wristwatch.
And it features most of
the elements that we introduced
earlier for UML state diagrams.
There are many more, but they
shall not be the topic here.