After we have dealt with
the types and characteristics of
models, it makes sense to
take a closer look at why
models are used in computer science.
So, why is there this
modeling lecture at all in the
context of computer science or
computer science-related courses of study?
And first of all, of course, the answer is
the same as mentioned before, in an earlier video.
So:
You want to design a system, understand
it better, visualize it, simulate it, etc.
And the same can be relevant
for computer science systems, of course.
And especially the more complex a
computer science system is going to be.
A system could, of course,
be a program, a database, virtual
reality environments (i.e.
also quite tangible systems).
And the more complex such a
system is, the more important it may
be to have a
plan before simply constructing it.
So, complexity plays a
role here, of course.
The same would be relevant
for other systems and models.
So depending on that, when it comes to
architecture, it depends a lot on what
kind of house you're planning to build.
If you're just building a doghouse, you might
not need to have a plan and a
3D model for it, you can
just go ahead and do it.
If, on the other hand,
you're thinking of building a single-family
home or a larger apartment complex
or a high-rise building, that's definitely
complex enough to warrant
and also require a plan.
Similarly, of course,
for information technology systems.
So a small script that is written once
certainly does not need to be modeled beforehand.
A more comprehensive program
or program system certainly does.
The goal and hope,
of course, is then that the
fact that one has modeled before one
begins to implement, leads to various advantages:
Avoidance of errors, better quality.
Lower costs due to
avoidance of repairs or wrong
ways, which one has to repeat then,
or to replace detours by new development.
Better documentation through models.
In an ideal case,
there's also an increase in reusability.
This does not mean that modeling
is always used in computer science.
So, there are some special situations.
Agile software development
is very modern.
There, models are partly dispensed with, or at
least they appear in a different form, more as
part of the development than
as a separate planning process.
In general, it should be
noted that modeling is certainly less
common in computer science
than in other engineering sciences.
So in architecture or mechanical engineering,
modeling is definitely done before implementation.
In computer science, this
is not always the case.
But in principle, the topic is
of course just as relevant here.
It may also be that the prevalence
in teaching is still somewhat stronger than
in practice, but this does
not have to remain so.
Several peculiarities of software also influence
the role of computer science models.
For indeed, there are differences between
designing and building a computer science
system and, for example, designing and
building a building complex in architecture.
One major difference is
that software is immaterial.
It is not so easy to determine how
much of a model has already been implemented.
This is, of course, quite different in architecture, where, if
you build a skyscraper and have a model, you can
also determine on the basis of
this model, by comparing it with reality:
How much has already been built?
How many floors have already been built?
Another point is that
software projects are usually unique.
Whereas in architecture, for example,
and also in many other engineering
fields, models also
have the role of serving as a
template for the purpose of multiple realizations.
In other words, a model is created in
order to be able to use the model as
a guide when large quantities of
an engine are to be produced.
In order to actually always build
the engine in the same way.
This is not the
case in software development.
Except, perhaps, in the context of
software product lines (which would
be a topic for the software engineering lecture), it
is the case that each software project is unique.
So, the model is not
there to be implemented multiple times.
Unlike in many other
areas, where, for example, in
architecture, 50 similar apartments are
to be created in a skyscraper.
Then the model, the plan, the 3D
plan is also good for ensuring that
the apartments on each floor actually
come out the same in the end.
This is not the
case in software technology.
So there are actually
differences compared to other areas.
And perhaps the second point is,
in a way, also a reason for reluctance to
always rely on models in
the practice of software development.
Then the question also arises:
Who is it that models, in
computer science, in the software development process?
The clear answer there is: it is unclear.
It depends on what kind of
software development process is being followed.
I just briefly
mentioned agile development.
There are also
classic software development processes.
If you are still
listening to Professor Heisel's software
engineering lecture, you will certainly
learn more about this there.
For example, in the waterfall model,
which is structured by phases, where
you can very clearly
determine where modeling happens.
This would be the
design phase in particular.
So, modeling is then really
an act that takes place separately
from implementation, from programming, and
also justifies its own role.
So, there might be the
programmer, the software developer, who implements.
And before that, there's the design
of the software architecture, or just the
design, and that's a design task that
a programmer doesn't necessarily have to do.
So, maybe that would also be
a role for Komedia graduates, for example.
And models are now explicitly popping up.
So at different levels,
models are created, and
then there are, for example, concrete
documents that you can also look at.
That would be the models in
such a procedure, maybe on different levels.
The result of the determination
of the requirements could be this
product requirements document, which
is a kind of model.
And then, during design, models are
created that are to be implemented later
and can be used for
comparison in later phases, for example.
Verification could then be to compare the
implementation against the model and to formally
ensure, by testing or by
proof, that there is a match.
This will not be a
topic of the lecture in particular.
So, we will mainly deal with
the formulation of the models and
statements, not
with the verification/testing.
That was just a
concrete model, a concrete process.
There are various other
ways to do software development.
Another way is iterative, where the
phases are not done once in a waterfall
fashion, but multiple phases are
done over and over again for
different prototypes, for different implementations
of the system being built.
And in each of these spirals in
this execution, modeling could also take place.
Because in each case,
new aspects are brought into
play. For example, the models
are refined to define more precise
requirements or additional requirements
for the next implementation cycle.
Of course, what you see
here are also just models.
So, perhaps no one is
going to proceed exactly like this.
What we see and have seen
are ultimately also models, so-called process models,
which abstract precisely from how
a concrete software development could happen.
And this does not capture
every detail of every possible software
development procedure or every concrete project that
might be carried out in a team.
But it does provide a
model for it, a simplified representation
that can be used as a guide.
We will not consider
such models any further because the process
models are also part of the
software engineering lecture with Professor Heisel.
I have already mentioned special cases.
So, in agile software development, modeling
is different, one could also say less.
Strictly speaking, models also appear
there, but rather in the later phases.
The models are rather short-lived.
They are used for test-driven
(instead of plan-driven) development, for example.
Other special cases would
be in open source software
development, where there are often many
different contributors working on a project.
Where somehow centralized modeling
could not be used at
all, but completely different
effects come into play.
On the other hand, there are also
development methods that are very strongly model-driven.
There is even the
term model-driven development, where
actually program code/software is to
be generated from the models.
So there are
different varieties, different manifestations.
As I said, this would be
a topic for the software engineering lecture.
What is relevant for us is:
There is a need for models
in different phases of software development.
And that's why this lecture will
just focus on these types of models.
Other important aspects when working with
models are, of course, questions like:
Is the model correct at all?
Is it consistent in itself?
Model correctness is, of course, difficult to
answer if you set up the model in
the first place in order to be aware of
what the system being developed should look like.
Then you don't really have a handle
on how to check it for correctness.
But for example, internal
consistency could be checked.
That should also come up in our example.
So correctness objectively would mean to check
somehow whether the system fulfills the purpose.
And that must depend on the
purpose, and is not necessarily clear
when the system is still being designed.
Internal correctness, on the other
hand, is quite testable or verifiable.
We will have, for instance,
in the model type of
Petri nets, certain properties that
a Petri net can have.
This then corresponds to
a certain absence of contradictions.
Liveness is also such a
concept, which is always meaningful.
One can also formulate a
problem for the model class itself.
For example, one
can determine general properties
for Petri nets, which one can check.
And if you now have or set up a concrete
model, then you can check
whether it has such a property.
And this is independent of the
concrete purpose of the system in question.
That's why we can perform certain
analyses on models that are useful
for a whole class of models.
This will not be in the
foreground, nor will it be the main part
of the lecture, but it will come up.
And, of course, in a
different context, when you really build the system
in the end, you can, of course, ask:
Does the model
match the later implementation?
That, too, will not be
so relevant for us here.
You would have to test or verify it.
That is not our main focus.
For some of these questions,
tools or software tools are used.
Be it for drawing,
for representing models, or
for switching between different
representations of a model.
For archiving, for code generation,
documentation, and of course for analysis.
Again, this will not take up
a lot of space in the lecture.
A few tools for use
in the lecture, especially for
the representation and partly also the simulation
of single models (especially for Petri nets),
can already be found as
suggestions in the Moodle course.
In the lecture itself, this will occur
most of the time, when I want to work
with Petri nets, and perhaps also in
video form, a simulation will be carried out.
From this, it is now a bit clearer
what the content of the course will be.
So, here's a brief overview.
It's not exactly in that order.
So, it's not chapters
that I'm going to follow.
However, the essential
things are mentioned here.
So we're going to need some
mathematical basics, of course, and develop
some of them, or I'll provide them,
without it being the first chapter right now.
One important type of description, which of
course has a mathematical basis, is graphs.
We have visual representation
models, and usually these will
be different kinds of graphs.
This can be relevant for
both static and dynamic system descriptions.
So a graph to describe the
relationships between subcomponents of a system would
then be relevant for static modeling.
Or for dynamic modeling, that
a graph represents, for example, flows,
represents processes in their order.
Graphs, of course, are a general concept.
And then beyond that,
there are Petri nets.
These are also graphs.
I had mentioned Petri
nets briefly for dynamic modeling.
So that will be a chapter in the lecture.
You may already have some
insight there from the pre-course.
I know that Petri nets are
sometimes treated there as an example.
Probably not in school computer science.
Petri nets will also be
interesting for us because, on
the one hand, they are well
suited to teaching certain concepts of distributed
systems such as concurrency,
conflicts, liveness, and so on.
On the other hand, Petri nets
are also a quite formal modeling tool.
That is, you should also see
how to deal with models formally.
Petri nets are very well suited for that.
There is also a bridge from Petri
nets to UML, to a subset of UML.
And there you will also see how
you can establish connections
between different modeling mechanisms.
How, for example, you can
systematically generate Petri nets from a
certain class of UML diagrams, and
then analyze them formally, for example.
UML itself might be known from
school, possibly also from the computer
science pre-course, at least in excerpts.
So, at least, class diagrams.
If you have covered object-oriented programming
in school in computer science classes,
then you have probably already
worked with UML, at least indirectly.
Both Petri nets and UML, you
may encounter further in your studies.
Of course, this specifically depends
on your course of study.
Petri nets are relevant in the context of
distributed systems and will certainly come up again.
UML used to be a
prominent part of the lecture Basic
Programming Techniques, because
Java was used.
Now, after the switch to Python,
it probably is at most on
the margins, if some Java is still
done at the end of the course.
On the other hand, UML will certainly
feature very prominently in the Advanced Programming
Techniques and Software
Engineering lectures as well.
Of course, it is the
case that we will mainly
deal with small models in
the course (for clarity/didactics of teaching).
Also said:
The use of models for the verification of
properties will not be central, but
will at least appear once in Petri nets.
We will, of course, do static and dynamic
modeling, especially in
the context of UML.
Both are not very formal there.
With Petri nets, more formal.
UML, as I already said
in the last video, is
a rather semi-formal modeling method.
Of course, even that, within this
scope, is by no means comprehensive;
it's not everything you can do in
computer science in terms of models.
The course is just an excerpt.
The modeling methods presented here
are not the only ones available.
The focus here is
on visual modeling using diagrams.
I had already mentioned that there
are, of course, also mathematical modeling, algebraic
modeling methods more
oriented to mathematical formula language.
We're going to do less of that.
A little bit in
describing operations, but by
no means to the extent that you could
also do that in a lecture like this.
At the end of this
video, a short word cloud.
It gives a good overview
of the content of the course.
These are simply several terms that were
collected from the slides of a previous
year, sorted by their frequency,
and then visualized here.
So here you see
some very prominent terms.
Of course:
"model," "modeling," "diagram" would
also show up here.
But I have taken them out.
They would have been too dominant,
because just because of this term down
here, it shows up almost on every slide.
Therefore, I had removed them.
Otherwise, if you then dive
into these terms, you will see
that certain things
are very prominent there.
Of course, the descriptive terms "Petri
net" and "UML" show up prominently.
You can see that we will
obviously be working a lot with examples.
That's why the word for "example" shows
up very often in the slides here.
Then there are more concrete terms like
"object" because we will be doing object-oriented
modeling to some extent.
"State."
That's obviously about static
modeling, the description of a
state, or dynamic modeling, the evolution
of the state of a system.
"Transition":
A term from dynamic modeling.
"Übergang":
As a German synonym for it.
In graphs, "nodes" appear
as parts of a graph.
And then more
specific terms like "region".
This is a concept that
appears in certain UML diagram types.
Activity diagrams are what
we're going to cover.
So you can get a little
bit of an initial sense here of
what we're going to be dealing with.
There are also terms that come
up that are not really relevant anymore:
Substitution I probably
won't look at explicitly.
That was also in
the context of object-oriented modeling.
The substitution principle, I'm not
going to focus on that anymore.
So again, you can't derive too
much from the word cloud either.
But a little bit of an impression
of what you can expect already emerges here.