Having dealt with graphs in
the last video, and having done
so using this little puzzle, this video will
on one hand be about something much
more specific to computer science, and on the
other hand, it won't be about graphs either.
I had said that we will be
doing a lot of modeling with graphs, but
we actually need (especially in preparation for
UML) one more ingredient that is textual.
Namely, static modeling of operations.
And that's what this video
is going to be about.
Because it's a prerequisite
and preparation for object-oriented class
design, or modeling classes
and especially their methods.
But we will get to that later.
First of all, generally,
and also detached from UML.
In fact, operations play a
role in mathematics as well as
in computer science, independent of object-orientation.
What are we talking about specifically,
also in the context of computer science?
Let's assume we want to
design a system in computer
science, be it a program or a database.
Then, often the first question is
which operations should
be offered and implemented.
And at least as importantly,
besides simply the names of operations,
also on which data they are to work.
This is about static modeling.
Ultimately, it is about
the structure of the system
or the functionalities and
services offered by the system.
So it is not about
what exactly the operations will do,
but first of all, for example, which
calls/uses should be syntactically allowed.
What, at all,
sensible operation uses should
be, and also how
operations can be combined.
Usually a system will
consist of many functionalities, which
may have to be used in combination.
And at least that
would be important for documentation.
So we can learn about
the system simply by capturing
this static information, even without
having to look at the implementation.
And ideally it would also
help with the implementation, for
example, by precisely recording which cases of
input have to be handled at all.
Or, by using consistency
checks to possibly avoid certain
errors, even before testing
or trying to prove anything.
Simply by having
recorded beforehand what the
operations are called (the names are
also important) but also on which
types of data they operate and
which combinations of operations should be allowed.
Then, during programming, during implementation,
errors can be uncovered that
might otherwise only be noticed during
operation or when the system has been
implemented and is to be tested.
I'll first explain with a very simple
example, so to speak
in a very simple domain.
Operations always refer to
a specific application area.
And the application domain
that you know from school,
where you have encountered
operations, is simply arithmetic.
So the arithmetic operations
are called: "plus", "minus", "times", etc.
These are, of course,
operations in this sense.
And depending on what we
then work with in a
system, we naturally have to
deal with more than just numbers.
But numbers will probably always
be involved in some way in a program.
So let's imagine, naively:
We might want to design a calculator app.
Then, the relevant operations we
probably want to offer are at
least the usual arithmetic operations.
And maybe we've decided that
we want to take the
set of natural numbers, including zero.
So we don't do fractional
numbers or floating point numbers first.
Then we could say:
Well, then addition is a binary
operation (because it takes two arguments,
namely a natural number twice
each) and returns a natural number.
This is set notation: a function.
A function, given its range of
values and its range of images.
The Komedia students should know this
as notation from the
second semester math lecture.
The computer science students
and the ISE students from
their respective courses where
set theory is taught.
Probably, for example, Discrete
Mathematics for the Applied Computer
Science students.
I assume that's where it comes in
as notation, very early in the semester.
Otherwise, at this moment, simply
an operation name "plus", two arguments,
each natural numbers
(N for natural numbers).
The result is also a natural number.
And of course:
If we have several operations
(one wants to have multiplication too,
for instance), then they have different
names (but here the same type, the
same information about
input and output values).
And, let's say, maybe division.
Subtraction could also be considered, but
already with division the question arises:
What type should the
output value be here, anyway?
And we could say:
Well, we know what division is.
But strictly speaking, at the
moment this is only information
about the parameters and the results.
So here also, if
we know "plus" as addition,
it is not yet
recorded what operations actually do.
Right now, we're trying to figure out
what their input and output ranges are.
And probably here, for example,
you would want to prohibit at
least division by zero, so that it
just can't be called with five and zero.
Because it says up here:
Let N be the set
of natural numbers including zero.
So you could decide here to say,
first (before deciding what the output range
will be) refine the
second input range a bit.
Restrict it a bit by saying:
We take there the set N+
as notation for only positive natural numbers.
Then, for example, one
would statically define the operation
to simply forbid the
second argument to be zero.
Then, of course, you can
use that in fewer situations.
You can still use
this for natural numbers that
are positive, but just not for
zero itself as a second argument anymore.
In the first position, you would
still be allowed to have zero.
So zero by five would go on.
Then you would have to somehow
think about the output range as well.
Above all:
What does one want here?
So if you have five and
three as arguments (which would each fit,
because three is a positive natural
number), what should the result be?
Should it be 1.666, or
maybe just 1 rounded down?
Does one do integer division, or
does one want to support rational numbers?
That is exactly the decision one
makes now in designing this operation.
Where you decide what
range you want here.
That would be the decision between:
I only allow natural numbers here.
Then I also have to allow zero because 0 /
5 = 0, and for five divided by three, I would want to
return 1 (so divide by
an integer and discard the remainder).
Or do I want to support rational numbers?
Then I would already have to provide here in
the static design of the operation
that rational numbers may be there.
Which of course contain the
natural numbers, but also
provide other candidates as outputs.
And perhaps one would even want both.
So the mathematicians like
to do that, of course.
They always use the same
symbol, overloaded in a certain sense,
so that it can depend, for example, on
the context, which expression exactly is
wanted (the integer or the non-integer).
And, of course, there is
no real "right" or "wrong",
no right or wrong decision.
It depends on the
purpose of the application.
So you can't say:
This is the right choice
and this is the wrong choice.
That would be nonsense.
Ultimately, it is precisely a part
of modeling to work out:
In the current application
context, what actually is
the desired area that should be here?
This could go as far as perhaps supporting
both and then providing suitable mechanisms in the
system so that this can be decided
in each case depending on the current situation.
Or at least one would have
to record which variants are available.
Of course, you also have to be careful
that if you take the rational numbers, for
example, you suddenly bring
a lot more into play.
Not only the rational numbers, i.e.
the fractional numbers, but also negative numbers.
Because the natural numbers, whether with or
without zero, were at least not negative.
If I choose the rational numbers here, I
would also have to deal with the fact
that I would then have negative numbers with
them (if I don't limit myself here to
only positive
and non-negative rational numbers).
So this is the decision
to make at these points.
And of course, once I've done that,
once I've introduced N+ or Q instead of
N, there's also the question
of what about the other operations.
So "plus" and so on, which before
was only in play for the natural numbers.
As soon as I have now
introduced, for example, this extra set,
in order to be able to deal with the
division by zero (by forbidding it), one also asks:
What about the operation
"plus" that existed before?
Does this perhaps also somehow
behave differently when one of the
two argument sets is replaced by N+?
So the next question would be:
What would happen now that we
have several different set ranges in play?
What does that mean for the
static information about the other operations?
Can we perhaps make those more precise as well,
or do we need to make any changes there?
In fact, in the specific case,
one can make them more precise.
Because you know:
If you have an addition and at
least one of the two summands is
positive, then the
result is also positive.
Before, it said: N and N goes to N.
Now we can additionally state:
If one of the two parameters, for example
the first one, is a positive number with certainty,
then after the addition, the
result will also be positive.
That is more information.
So, statically, we then know more about the
result than before, where there was only N here.
That would also have allowed
zero to come out there.
This will not happen if at least one
of the two arguments certainly is not zero.
Of course, this could be done in
the same way for the other position.
And one could also hold,
for the multiplication for example,
that if both arguments are
positive, the result is also positive.
But of course, not this
information, because it would be wrong.
It is not true that a positive number
multiplied by a natural number is always a positive number.
So here there is
really potential for distinction
between the operations, which can and
should be held on this operation.
So then we haven't quite
defined exactly what multiplication does.
But this restriction, that unlike for addition, not
simply the fact that one of the
arguments is positive is enough for the
result to be positive as well, that
can already be held here as
a distinction between these two operations.
Why all this?
Because on the basis
of this static information,
i.e., without having an implementation of
the operation (without really calculating anything),
we can already determine
whether certain expressions, certain terms,
certain formulas, which can be written
down, are okay or not okay.
We have two formulas here that simply
consist of these operations that
have been introduced so far.
And if you were to
work those out, you would find
that this gives you
a number that makes sense.
Here it comes: five plus zero is five, times
four is twenty, and then we can calculate three
by twenty.
Whether dividing by an integer or
not, at least a result is returned.
Whereas with this expression, if
you wanted to work it
out, you would run into division by zero.
But the point is:
With the static information that was
on the slides before, you can tell
that this expression is not
safe even without calculating it out.
Because you don't have a value from N+
standing here, you could use the information,
with this refinement
of multiplication here,
to determine that it's not
possible to type this expression.
So, to use the
operation with the information
that is here about the parameters
and results to type this expression.
So you could statically prevent this
expression from being written down at all.
And then you also know that at runtime,
at the time when the system is supposed
to operate dynamically, there is
no division-by-zero error, for example.
And the point here is, of course:
Sure, I could calculate
something for the numbers,
but in general, I
don't have concrete numbers.
In general, I might have an expression
that depends on variables in the program.
Then I couldn't say anymore:
I'll calculate this for a test to
see if a division by zero comes out.
If we have static information
about operations and about the
variables, we can make such a distinction
even if we have unknowns
there and therefore cannot calculate concretely.
That is the purpose of this
kind of static information for operations.
Now it is like this:
For these arithmetic operations, you might
think, "Yes, what do we gain here?"
That's just school arithmetic.
We know what it means to
have a zero in division, for example.
That this is a problem.
But the point is, this
handling of such arithmetic expressions,
or terms as they
are called, is more general.
While you may know this from school, having also worked
with such terms and transformed them, it is interesting
from a modeling point of view that
such an algebraic approach (i.e., describing
the operations through their signatures, input and
output formats and the rules according to which terms
are set up), is not
only possible for arithmetic operations on numbers.
But in general, for operations
in practically any other application
domains, one has to deal with other sets,
other operation names, and new questions
about which combinations
should be allowed.
If you model this precisely, then you
have already recorded certain information about the
respective application domain before you
start to implement something.
That should be the goal
here when specifying such operations.
Now I'll provide an example, and
a different example than the arithmetic operations.
So let's imagine, as another domain,
that we want to do vector graphics.
So maybe we would like
to develop a graphics program or
somehow an app that should have
operations to draw and manipulate images.
And we want to model that program now.
That means we're still
going to have numbers, but
we're now not *just* dealing with mathematical
number domains like we just did, but
we have to work with
other domain-specific types as well.
So for number domains, we could now
take mathematical notation like we just did.
Maybe you learn in parallel,
in the GPT lecture
(depending on your course of
studies), the programming language Python.
There are also special
data types, for example, the
number types for integers and for
floating point numbers, i.e., decimal numbers.
Maybe also strings, because you want
to have the output in text form.
And now, here we would want
to introduce more domain-specific types
that are not necessarily
in the programming language,
but that we need to
support our vector graphics domain.
So, what do we
need in the graphics domain?
Perhaps colors, points, coordinates,
or even whole images.
So, let's think
about an initial operation.
What might we have as
an operation that creates an image?
Maybe we would like to be able
to paint a circle as an image.
And then we need to think about:
What parameters does that need?
At least a radius.
We could also say, maybe a color.
But we could also say:
First of all, a circle by itself is simply
specified by the fact that there is a radius.
And that could also be a decimal number.
That's why we introduce an operation
called "circle" which takes a number, interprets
that number as a
radius, and returns an image.
We could imagine that if we
call "circle" as an operation with the
argument 3, then this
picture should be created.
I will now always show
such pictures here on the right,
as an idea of
what the operations should do.
But the modeling itself
does not contain this information.
Here, it is only about this:
There is this "circle" operation, which
takes a number and delivers an image.
The fact that it is this image, in this specific
case, would not be part of the static modeling,
but already part of the dynamic modeling.
But maybe this helps a little bit to
understand what I
want with the operation.
Although I will always show such examples,
the focus is actually on these operation
names and their signatures
(information about inputs and outputs).
Here, it should be noted that 3
is, of course, an integer and not a
comma, but nevertheless may be used here,
too, if comma numbers are allowed here.
Because in the end, the set of decimal
numbers is a superset of the set of integers.
So, every integer is, of
course, also a "decimal number".
So you don't have to write
3.0 here, you can take 3 directly.
At least that's how I write
it down now in my example domain.
That would be a first operation.
This alone would not be super exciting.
You could exactly paint circles,
or always exactly one circle.
This then would be a picture.
Of course, we don't want to leave it
at that, we want to somehow provide for
a few more operations when
we design our vector graphics app.
And for example, we could start
to simply allow different geometric shapes.
For example, you want to
be able to draw a rectangle.
You'd have to think about:
What are the parameters for that?
There would have to be two now.
There is no radius, but
perhaps a width and a height.
And the result is again a picture.
The interpretation would be that if I,
for example, call "rectangle" with 7 and 5,
I get such a rectangle.
There is already an interpretation in there,
namely, that the first argument should be interpreted
as the width, and the
second argument as the height.
That is not in this specification here.
As static information, it only contains:
There are two floating-point arguments.
And not how they exactly contribute
to the picture in the end.
What one could also ask here, in
the sense of the arithmetic example domain before:
What happens if one
of the arguments is zero?
Even with the
circle, one might ask:
What if the circle is called with
the argument zero or even with negative radii?
This could have been countered
by deliberately introducing another set with
only non-negative floating point numbers.
Or one could then make
decisions in the implementation on how
to deal with such edge cases.
So maybe:
A "circle" of size zero
would simply be a point.
A rectangle of height zero
would simply be a horizontal line.
And for example, for
negative arguments, either always say
they are not accepted, or
they are treated like zero.
That is not expressed here.
Here, we are first concerned with what combinations
are allowed in principle, syntactically so to speak.
A few more examples.
What could be further operations?
One could introduce another square.
Maybe you don't need it, because you
can represent a square as a rectangle.
But it might
become other general operations.
For example, you might want to
draw general paths, that is, any sequences
of strokes that don't exactly
make a box like this rectangle.
What do you need as arguments?
Some kind of coordinates, i.e., points.
A point as a combination
of x and y values.
And for a path, you need several points.
So maybe a list like that, a
listing of several pairs of coordinates like that.
You could say:
A path has a list as an argument.
This is now to be
indicated here by these square brackets.
And in this list,
coordinate pairs can be present.
So (-1,0) would be the first point here, x-axis
-1, y-axis 0, and the next point would be here.
So behind the dot, dot, dot,
there would be other
such pairs, for example (1,2).
Here, there seems to be
(3,0) and then here, (6,4).
So, I call the path operation
with such a list of coordinate pairs,
and then an image comes out.
In that case, just this zigzag curve.
And maybe also as another operation:
Suppose we also want to allow
labels in our images, somehow with text.
Then we have to have an
operation that converts text into an image.
And that could be,
for example, simply like this:
The name "print" might be quite obvious.
And the argument to that operation
would be a string, a text.
And the result would be
a picture representing that text.
So, for example, print("ABC").
You probably know these quotation marks
as well, as delimiters for strings
in many programming languages (or in
the programming language you currently learn).
And then the result here will be
a picture that contains exactly the text ABC.
So, we could do a
few things with that now.
Strictly speaking, we could either draw
a circle or draw a rectangle,
or draw any sequence of strokes
like that, or output a string.
Now we would like
to have more flexibility.
For example, this string
here is very small now.
Maybe you'd rather
have it displayed larger.
We have designed the print operation in such a way
that it does not specify (as an argument, for example)
what font size you
want to print this with.
We could revise that and say:
Let's introduce an argument here.
Then we still wouldn't have the
ability to resize other
graphical objects, for example.
So, more general, perhaps,
would be to say:
Outputting a string is always
done in some fixed font size.
But if we want a string to be displayed
larger, there is another operation for
that, which can enlarge any image.
Also including images created using "print".
If we decide this way, it
would mean that we would introduce an
operation (and even several
operations) to manipulate existing figures.
In the operations we have seen so
far, Picture only ever appeared as a result.
We put a number in, get a picture.
We plug in two numbers, get a picture.
We plug in a list
of points, we get a picture.
We put in a string, we get a picture.
If we want to go beyond
that, we could provide operations that
have images as inputs as well.
And for example, for this
scaling, for resizing, we could say:
We'd like to have
an operation called scale.
It gets an image, gets two
numbers to be interpreted as scale.
Enlargement or reduction, depending on whether it
is greater than 1 or less than 1.
So there should be one
factor each, in x- and y-direction.
Then we could say:
Well, if we take the picture, which
results from print("ABC") (that would be this
small picture here), and we scale that by the
factor 3 in both x and y direction, then
we get exactly this larger ABC typeface.
That would be one
way of manipulating existing figures.
We can think of others.
For example, if we want
to color the text as
well, or color other figures, maybe
a "color" operation would be good.
It has to get an image again, and
it has to get a color passed to it.
So there has to be
a supply of colors somehow.
That's just a new set
that would be defined somewhere.
And the result would be a picture again.
And then we could say, for example:
Take the image from just
now (even before scaling, that
is, the little string
"ABC"), and color it red.
Then you get this result.
And wanted would be, of course, if we
combine this, call both "scale"
and "color" (use nested operations),
then we should get the big string in red.
The idea, then, is to
get an image out of here
that can be used again
as an argument for this.
We could, of course, combine these
operations, just as in arithmetic we can
put "plus" and "times" and
"division" etc. into each other.
And get bigger and bigger expressions, which
are more complicated, but can be evaluated
with the definitions of the single
operations, by doing several calculation steps.
What else can we want?
Scaling, coloring.
Rotation, for example.
Our rectangles earlier
were always axis-parallel.
Maybe we want to
have rectangles that are skewed.
Then we would need
the ability to rotate an image.
So we could say:
Our rectangle from before, that
would be the expression "rectangle(7,5)".
We'd like to rotate that by an angle.
Then we would have to somehow capture, or
decide, how to interpret that angle.
Let's assume we measure angles simply
in degrees and not somehow in radians.
Then 30 just corresponds to a
rectangle tilted about this angle here, with
the rotation always taking
place about the origin.
So, what can we do now?
Now, we have these images that
we can change a little bit.
But they're always
centered around the origin.
Which also means, for example, that rotating
a circle makes no sense at all.
Because the circle was
formed around the origin.
If we rotate it now, and
this always happens around the origin,
one can do nothing else with the
circle than paint it and color it.
You could scale it and
make it an ellipse by
scaling it differently
in the x- and y-directions.
But you can't, for example, draw
it in any place other than
the origin of the coordinate system.
This is certainly unattractive
for a general graphics app.
So, we should have at least
one more operation that allows us
to draw objects at some
place other than the origin.
And if we would also let all
strings we want to print always overlap at
the origin, we wouldn't be
able to read anything at all.
So, what do we need for this?
Another operation to move an image.
What does it need as arguments?
First, the image to be moved,
and then probably two parameters again.
Like here for the x- and y-directions,
but just not as scaling factors, but
as displacement values.
And the result would
be an image, of course.
So the idea is:
If we take a circle with
a radius of 3 and shift it in
the x-direction by 2 and in the y-direction
by 1, we get the same shape,
the same circle, but it
is now in a different position.
And the circle
is then completely shifted,
which is why the centre would
now be at this new position (2,1).
Then we could draw individual
shapes of our choice, our
size, our color, our choice of position.
However, we could not
combine any of these.
For example, we could not yet
draw an image containing both a circle
and a rectangle in this way.
With the operations we have so far,
we would only ever be able to
paint single geometric shapes
and position them somewhere.
So, what else would we need?
What else would be conceivable
or desirable as a meaningful operation?
Anything that would allow
us to combine multiple images.
And the easiest choice would
be to introduce a binary
operation, like the "plus" in numbers ("+"
takes two numbers and returns one number).
We've only ever had operations until now
that took at most one
image and returned one image.
If we want to
combine images, maybe overlap
them, we need an operation that
composes an image from partial images.
This could be a
binary operation with two arguments,
each Pictures, and it
should return a Picture.
What would be a reasonable use for it?
For example, we could
form the following expression:
So somehow a path,
which we have seen before.
We color it blue.
Because we may combine the operations.
That would be a picture expression.
And we get another image expression by
outputting a piece of text, coloring it, rotating
it appropriately, and then moving it
from the origin to a different location.
And then we would have an image that
corresponds to this blue zigzag line, and an
image that corresponds to
this cleverly positioned text.
And if we combine that with this
new operation, then we get an image that
has both in it.
And now, with these ingredients and
the arbitrary nesting of operations (as we're
already seeing here), we can already
create quite complex and interesting images.
One thing to note is that
this new operation is now
used as an infix operation.
That is, unlike "move"
and "color" etc, it is
no longer used with
parentheses around its arguments.
Instead, you simply write
them between two terms.
Just as you are
used to in mathematics,
from arithmetic, that the "plus" is
simply infixed between two numbers.
So infix in the sense of
"between the operands", between the arguments.
Instead of as in "move", "rotate", etc.,
that you write the arguments in parentheses.
This is a common usage,
especially of such symbol operations.
In doing so, one can also ask oneself:
For example, can I apply
the operation to three images?
Probably not directly, because here
it says: there are two images.
But like I can write down
"plus": 2 + 5 + 4.
Then I have added three numbers,
although "plus" is a binary operation.
But again, could I combine more
than two pictures by simply writing: this
picture, operation symbol, next picture,
operation symbol, next picture again, etc.
For the Komedia students, for
example, as a reminder of
the Mathematical Structures
lecture, where we
considered monoids; that was
about associative operations in algebra.
Here, you would expect that
to be such an associative operation.
The other students certainly know
associativity at least as a
property of "plus" or "times".
So then, it's okay to use
this operation symbol even if we
want to combine more than
two pictures in a row.
So, now, I just designed
some operations and showed some examples.
Of course, I won't do an implementation of
them now, that's not what this is about.
But what is interesting and important here,
and why we introduced this, is that
we can recognize certain calls/combinations
of operations as useful or
not useful based
on such static information.
That's the aspect I mentioned before.
That such static information can serve to
exclude certain potential errors, ultimately,
already in the modeling, so
that they can no
longer occur in the implementation.
Typical examples would be the following:
For example, it makes no sense for the
operation introduced by me to
write something like "circle(circle(3))" here.
So, "circle(3)" is
a meaningful expression.
We even saw earlier the
picture that emerges when I interpret that.
But it doesn't make sense to
write "circle" again because of that.
Why not?
Because "circle", according to the signature I had at the
front of the slide, expects a number as an argument.
Which is true here for this expression.
But for the outer call, the argument
is not a number, but an image.
Because 3 is a
number, "circle(3)" is then a
picture, and I can't put a
picture as an argument into "circle".
That would be the argument here
why this expression would not be okay.
Why that's rejected, just
based on the static information.
In the implementation, if we use
a programming language that takes into
account such signatures of operations, we would
expect an error message from the compiler.
That it says:
This expression makes no
sense, I refuse to
even create a program for
it, which would then be executable.
And you can think of various other cases
that are okay and that are not okay.
On the slide, I've listed a
few cases that are not okay.
Each with a short intuitive explanation
as to why this expression would not be okay.
This expression would not be okay
because "circle(3)" is again an image,
and that itself is not printable text.
So "print" expects a string,
a string like text, which
is then converted to an image.
I can't pass a completed picture
to "print".
Then "print" would not
know what to print.
It would not, as the operations are
interpreted here, print
the text "circle(3)" somehow.
For that, it would have
to be enclosed in quotation marks.
Yes, "print" can print any text, but
it would have to be clear somehow,
by quotation marks, that
you really have a
string there and not another expression
to be interpreted as an image.
For the same reasons, something
like "print(3)" would not be okay,
at least in my interpretation.
There are programming languages where, if
there is a 3, it would just
be silently implemented
as the string "3".
I don't want to allow that here.
I had imagined strings
and numbers as different
things, respectively
named them differently.
That is, "print(3)" would not be a
valid expression here in my example domain
now, because it is not true that
the 3 is a string by itself.
For that, it would have
to be enclosed in quotation marks.
And for none of these observations
here, do I have to somehow run
the program and paint the
things, that is, create images.
I can already determine all
that from the static information.
Here's another mistake.
Here's the error: we applied
"print" to a string, and
an image comes out, here I'd like
to scale it by a factor of 3.
Why is this still wrong?
Because this has the
wrong number of arguments.
I introduced up front:
"scale" always takes two arguments in addition
to the image, i.e. two numbers, to
be able to scale in x and y directions.
If I forget one of
them, I would expect that
to be a non-valid expression here.
So even if you only want
one factor to scale, you have to
specify it twice to use it
for both x and y directions.
For coloring, we need an
image and a color to use.
But it was specified as:
You specify the image
first and then the color.
And if I do that the wrong way around,
I would expect that to be rejected here as well.
Again, more of an
error like the one above.
So "rotate" expects an
image and an angle,
rather than two angles or
anything that is a number.
Here in front, there should be an image,
and the number 30 itself is not an image.
You can print 30 with "print("30")", and then you
would have an image that you could rotate.
But the number 30 itself is not
an image and therefore cannot be rotated.
Our combination operator was
meant for images.
So as was said, the specification was
for a Picture and also a Picture, and
the result would be a Picture.
For "ABC" and "DEF", you could imagine
that you want to pack them together somehow.
Maybe you want to
get the string "ABCDEF".
For this, one would have
to introduce another operation, however.
The operation "and" with this symbol
was introduced as an operation between pictures.
And "ABC" as well as
"DEF" are just not pictures.
So we have a whole set of errors,
which one could exclude, simply
by adhering to the operation signatures.
Conversely, of course, this does not mean
that all programming errors are automatically detectable.
So for instance, with the
rectangle operation, the requirement was:
You have to specify two numbers.
And I had interpreted the first number
as width and the second as height.
But of course, this is not in
the signature, in this
specification on the corresponding slide.
Here, from this, you can't tell what
the height is and what the width is.
That is:
Even if I actually want to
draw a rectangle that is wider than it is high,
like this, but accidentally
write "rectangle(5,7)" instead of "rectangle(7,5)",
that would be an error
that cannot be detected statically.
Because the role of these two
arguments isn't fixed by
the static information from the previous slides.
That is:
An error that I make there is simply
an error that I would notice only dynamically at
runtime, at execution time
of my app / program.
But a whole series of
possible errors is already caught statically.
And depending on the programming language, more
or less of such errors are acceptable here,
of course, or are
waved through, so to speak.
So in Python,
"print(3)" would probably work.
That would simply be interpreted.
In my domain here, I had
specified that I don't want that.
So, there has
to be a string explicitly.
That's practically the end of this part.
One little comment, one little
note, I would like to make.
And that is for those of you
who know programming languages like C or Java.
That's not necessarily the case for all of
you, because, for example, the programming introduction at our
school is now with Python,
for Komedia and Applied Computer Science.
But if you know C or
Java from school, for example, then on
the one hand, you understand the concept
of such operations, such specifications of signatures.
On the other hand, you
know a different syntax for it.
So there it is
not specified so mathematically.
Therefore, a small slide, where
simply this connection is made, how
these correspond to each other.
So this "rectangle" operation,
for example, which I
have defined or declared, is passed
two numbers and returns an image.
In C or Java, and many
other mostly object-oriented or simply imperative programming
languages, it would correspond to
a declaration of the following kind
(if they are typed programming languages):
The name "rectangle" would be used
here as the name of a function.
The result type, i.e., what output
comes out (which is the last quantity
here in mathematical notation),
is then often specified first.
So, "rectangle" returns an image and
gets the arguments passed to it,
which are here to the left of the arrow.
So, here we see that
two floating point numbers are passed.
And often a name for the
parameters is given directly
in the programming language.
This provides a little bit
more information, if x and
y are interpreted geometrically as
the x and y coordinates.
There could be arbitrary names for
it, but of course, names
are gladly assigned which already say something
about the intention of the operation
and the use of the arguments.
So, this is noted here simply because
many of you may
know this kind of notation.
And then, you should just be able to match it
very directly to how I just declared the operations here
now in the slides, and how it's going
to happen in the corresponding exercise as well.
So, that's almost the same
information, just written down differently.