So, we have just seen this example.
And I had already made a few
hints in the direction of Petri nets.
And in fact, in what follows, we're
going to compare the individual elements of
activity diagrams, their constituents, to
Petri net constituents, borrowing from
a semantics found in the literature
for at least parts of activity diagrams.
We're not going to use that in the
sense of really examining that semantically, but we're
going to use that correspondence to explain
the activity diagram elements in the process.
And we'll always do that
for the individual elements in general,
but also related to this example.
214 # slide
O.k., so basically this then
gives us a way to translate
activity diagrams into Petri nets.
Just as we had translated Petri
nets with capacities into Petri nets
without capacities and through this, of
course, one can then understand activity
diagrams, because we know for Petri
nets what the respective meaning is.
Okay, so what are the first
kind of nodes in activity diagrams?
Those were these action
nodes or simply actions.
They're these ovals or
rectangles with rounded corners.
So these kind of nodes that looked
like that in the diagram as well.
So the "create plan" was such a
first, such an action node or action.
O.k. and that corresponds very directly
in Petri nets simply to transitions.
In Petri nets, transitions looked like
this and could have a name.
So so an action from
an activity diagram would just be
a transition with the appropriate
name in a Petri net.
And because it's about action, you
could take as such an indication
that you usually then have names there
that somehow correspond to activities or verbs.
Yes, like here "creating".
Okay, the intuition is
that actions stand for activities.
Something that takes time.
Yes, we think again of workflow,
so to speak, the
description of successive individual steps.
Then each individual step is
something that is somehow an activity.
Which perhaps takes a while, which represents
an action, like the transitions in Petri nets.
So, that would just be
a different representation, so to speak.
So that's still quite simple.
Actions are transitions.
Okay, then there were
the connections between actions.
Those were these arrows.
215 # slide
That would be the control flow
or at some point then object flow.
If we have object nodes, we will take
the tokens then not only simply as markers.
As markers where the focus
is in the activity diagram.
But actually, like
in the house construction
example a token stands for a
concrete plan, thus for an object.
Something that is also perhaps related
to a class and object diagram.
Then we're talking more about the
object flow.
But the point is: There is this flow,
primarily between actions.
How can we represent that in a Petri net?
Well, in the Petri
net, after all, there can
be no connection, no linkage
from a transition to a transition.
Yes, if we translate action as
transitions, then "Choose building site" would
be a transition, "Find architect"
a transition, then there can't be
a direct connection, as
here in the activity
diagram, because in Petri nets transitions
and places must always occur alternately.
Therefore there will be
a so called auxiliary place here (elsewhere later also auxiliary transitions).
So on the Petri net side there
is a place, which does not get
a name, which is not directly motivated by
anything that occurs here in the activity diagram.
It is simply there to establish
the connection between these two actions or
on the Petri net
side between these two transitions.
Because such a process could be, if
somehow "select building site" has fired, I
would put down a token, a marker.
And then this transition could
fire and pass this token.
And then could fire "create plan"
and again somehow still have an output.
So then this sequence of individual
steps in the activity diagram would correspond
to the sequential
firing of these transitions.
And for this they
should be linked meaningfully
and this is easily done
here by such mediating auxiliary places.
Yes, so of course these
edges/these arrows then correspond to
the temporal logical sequence of
the order in which things happen.
And auxiliary places are that because
they are only there to produce
this legality of the Petri net.
They also do not have their own name.
We had that already several times that
we could not necessarily give a meaningful
name to all elements in Petri net.
These three transitions would have a
meaningful name here, because they correspond to
these actions, and these are auxiliary places, because
they are simply there to get the flow correct
and not because they correspond to
anything directly from the activity diagram.
They don't deserve their own name,
so to speak, and we've seen something
similar in Petri nets for transitions.
So auxiliary transitions that
didn't have their own name
because, for example, they don't correspond here
exactly to an action from the activity diagram.
Ok, so actions become transitions.
Control flow can be realized by
inserted places and the respective connections.
216 # slide
Then in the activity diagram that
we had seen, there were these object
nodes or one such object node.
That was another kind of
node in the activity diagram.
Also represented differently
in a rectangle
without rounded corners,
so an actual rectangle.
Intuitively, from the point of view of
understanding, these stand, so to speak, for
a storage location, for a
storage for objects, concrete objects.
Quite understandable in the
sense of object-oriented modeling.
So, if we imagine that we might use an
activity diagram to describe
or model a software system.
Modeling an aspect of it, then
there might actually be a class name
here, from a class
diagram, which we developed earlier.
And the idea would then be that the
objects that are here, that the marking/tokens then stand
for, that they should actually
be instances of the particular class.
That doesn't show up in the example now
because we don't have a class diagram in mind.
But the intuition would be that
such an object node could actually
be used to store
concrete instances of classes.
And these just correspond to
normal places in the Petri net.
In the Petri net, if we wanted to
store resources somehow, we use places for that.
So this object node would become a place in
the Petri net and it would have a name.
So it's not just an auxiliary
place, it's a real named place.
Logically it gets the same
name as this object node.
And if there would be
for example here now several possibilities,
from which somehow a plan can result.
Then this would correspond to the
fact that there are several transitions, several
actions from the activity diagram translated
into transitions in the Petri net.
Several transitions that can
deposit tokens on this place.
So somehow a management of resources and
for that we had stored
tokens on places in Petri nets.
From this part of the activity diagram then
this part of a Petri net with these
two actions becoming transitions and this
object node realized by a named place.
The names of such places or of
object nodes are usually nouns and not verbs.
Yes, because it is just about
objects that can be put there.
O.k., I had already
indicated that a moment ago.
So, if we were
actually doing software modeling,
then such object nodes would
often be labeled with class names.
Because the intuition then is that
that makes the connection between the
static modeling and the dynamic modeling.
The static modeling, which describes
the classes and objects, and the dynamic
modeling, which then describes sequences
of actions and can use
that there are these object
types from the static modeling.
I.e. not that these
object nodes have somehow
attributes, as we have
assigned attributes to classes.
Because this node should
not be an object,
but this should be
a storage for different objects.
So it would make no sense to
structure this node somehow and to write
attribute values into it, for example.
Because it is only a storage
for concrete objects and not an object.
O.k., what else did we
have in our example activity diagram.
217 # slide
Well we still had this kind of node.
I hadn't given them a name yet,
they are called "decision nodes".
In the example, we had made
a decision like that there as well.
That was after "creating a plan".
There, we wanted to submit it
and there should then be the possibility
that either the plan is accepted or not.
And that led to
various further processes, ultimately
a branching in the flow,
in the control or object flow.
Where out of alternative paths,
exactly one is always chosen.
So no splitting of
control flow or of tokens,
but actually a choice of one path.
O.k., for this these
diamond nodes are used,
which can have several inputs or outputs.
And possibly have such
conditions at the exits.
What would be the
equivalent in a Petri net?
Well, if we want to
somehow branch a path in
the Petri net, we can do that by
branching from a place where a token could be.
Like for example here the
submitted plan, have several possible exits,
so have several possible transitions, each
having this place as a precondition.
In that case, if this is the
transition to this action node and then we
want to have further flow here and here,
then we couldn't have two exit
arrows directly from the transition somehow.
Because that would mean that we're splitting
something up, so we're outputting two tokens.
No, there is a place (that does NOT count as auxiliary place) where
this action, this transition puts a token.
And then there could also be different transitions
here and here, each of which can consume
this token and then have some
flow in this direction or that direction.
So, if here below an activity
diagram is translated into further transitions,
then the first of them
could be the output here.
O.k. it can be, we even see
that in the example here, that we
now have to
introduce auxiliary transitions.
So then this place ensures that
we can have such a branch.
We couldn't do that directly.
Yes, if we did the same here too, if there
followed another node like that in the example,
then we couldn't just say
we'll replace it again with
a place like this node
and have a direct connection.
That is not possible.
Because of the rules of
Petri net again, that there
can be only connection from places
to transitions and transitions to places,
then we must introduce an
auxiliary transition at this point.
It doesn't get a name either, it
is only there to make this further transport
of a token from here to here in
a way that is legal for a Petri net.
And not just have a
connection from place to place.
Which would not be a valid Petri net.
This can occur here
for example, because a
decision node is followed by
another decision node or an
object node, which would also be
realized by a Petri net place.
In the same way this can
be also with the reverse order.
So not only with following but
also with preceding decision or object nodes.
And also the merge nodes
which we will see shortly.
Strictly speaking, this is
not a branching node
but a merge node
in the concrete activity diagram.
That's what this one was.
What I'm describing is the
path from here to here.
So from this element to this element.
This is a branching node,
because one input, two outputs, and
this is a merge node,
because two inputs and one output.
And there it just can't be from
this place, which we had already seen, which
we had already described on a
slide, how this part of the activity
diagram becomes a Petri net part.
There it became a place.
And then there can't be a direct
connection from this place to this place.
In between, there must
be an auxiliary transition
in the Petri net, so
to speak, drawn somewhere here.
And it would be just
this one in the concrete example.
O.k., then we have what else?
218 # slide
I would like to make
a few remarks at this point.
I have already said this several times.
Namely, this reason, essential reason, for
this introduction of auxiliary places and auxiliary
transitions is simply that in the end
a structurally correct Petri net should come out.
In which places and transitions occur
alternately and for this one must
add further elements if necessary, which
were not visible at all in the
activity diagram, because other elements occur in it.
O.k. I had also just indicated that.
So what was just in
those square brackets: "accepted", "not accepted".
So finally the control
at the branch in which
direction the control or
object flow should go.
The so-called "guards",
of course, somehow refer to
knowledge from the application domain.
They are not described in
more detail in the activity diagram.
So, they should not logically overlap.
So it makes sense to
have something like "accepted", "not accepted".
Because these are
exactly opposite statements,
so they neither
overlap nor forget anything.
Of course, at such
a node it should always
be clearly possible to
choose the next/appropriate exit.
But that is no
longer part of the activity
diagram, to elaborate on
how that is somehow determined.
For example, if there are
objects moving through the activity diagram.
Object flow, you could
imagine that those are conditions
that then actually refer
to attributes of those objects.
Maybe checking some Boolean conditions.
But we won't do
that in such detail, because
we are more concerned with
the structural properties of activity diagrams
and not with now a
concrete binding to a software system.
In normal Petri nets we do
not specify such conditions, because that
would be outside the
semantics of Petri nets.
Okay, and that would still be
relevant if we wanted to consider
such outflow processes
quantitatively, such control flows.
So the actions, I had
said, these are activities that
cost time.
And these control elements,
so either the distribution nodes
or others we will see shortly,
of these one assumes
that they simply happen immediately.
They are just there to somehow
influence the direction
in which the flow takes place.
They themselves are not meaningful
actions/activities/verbs
that somehow require extra time as steps.
That would be relevant, if
one wanted to use such
an activity diagram
to make quantitative statements.
But we will not do that either.
O.k. let's discuss some more elements.
219 # slide
We had one more element,
which were the merge nodes.
They were also represented
like this, with this diamond.
But in contrast to the "decision nodes",
these are nodes where
different flows come together.
So here there are
two inputs and one output.
They bring together alternative
control or object flows.
In the Petri net these
would again simply be places (that do NOT count as auxiliary places).
Here it is also the case that if I
have a place and there is an arrow to
it from two different directions of
transitions, then it can be that in
this case a token comes from the
left or a token comes from the right.
In both cases there would be a token here
afterwards which could be passed on
to the following transitions standing here.
So this would serve to merge such
a flow, from here or from here,
for continuation then in this
part of the Petri net.
O.k. of course in
the postcondition of different transitions,
if necessary, auxiliary transitions can be placed
on the left and on the right.
Depending on what happened here in
the activity diagram at these two arrow
ends or places/positions from which these
arrows go out in the activity diagram.
O.k. there are not only
exactly branching or merge nodes.
There is also, so to speak, the common
case, where we have such a diamond, in which
perhaps, for example, two
inputs and two outputs occur.
Yes, this is also legal.
That can also happen, can also occur.
And also this is translated
simply by a place, which
then has, perhaps
in the postcondition, several transitions
and at the same time
also in the precondition several transitions.
So, for example, a place where there are arrows
coming in here from the top and from the left.
And for example arrows going out
to the right and arrows going down.
So, that also fits with the
elements that exist in Petri nets.
Okay, what else did we
have in the activity diagram?
Well we still had these two graphical
elements that I haven't said anything about yet.
Yes everything else that we see
here, we have now already worked through.
Yes well, except for the
start and the end as well.
Those are the things
we still have to describe.
220 # slide
O.k. first of these comes
the fork or also parallelization node.
That was exactly the moment/the place/the
position in the activity diagram, where such
a flow split, in the example,
that I had carried out live.
Where I had let the
tokens wander through the network.
So that's a place where a control
flow or an object flow is split
into several parallel
flows, parallel, concurrent.
How can you do that?
What corresponds to that in a Petri net?
Well a transition with multiple outputs.
So let's imagine there's
a token coming here.
And it's supposed to become two
different flows here, then that can be
realized by a transition that consumes
that one token, but outputs two tokens.
That would lead to after
that, whatever other parts are coming
down here, that they can both fire,
the transitions that occur in here, because
both here and here there is a token.
So forkings in the activity diagram
become transitions in the Petri net
with multiple places in the postcondition.
Of course, these can
also be auxiliary places.
That depends again on what other
activity diagram parts follow here.
Maybe there is an action node directly
here, then this would be a transition.
But we can't fire from
a transition directly to a transition, so then we
have an auxiliary place here and
only after that comes the Transition, which
corresponds to the action node, which
perhaps occurred here on the left side.
And the same could happen
here in the right flow.
Ok, these are again such unnamed
transitions, they don't get a name.
We can put a fork here, but in
the activity diagram they don't have a name either.
There the actions have names,
which then become named transitions.
Okay, and now, as
with the branch and merge
nodes/branch and join nodes, there is a
counterpart to this element, so to speak.
So to the forking belongs dually the
merge or synchronization node, where just such
two flows that have been
created here are brought together again.
221 # slide
So merges or "join node" that would
be where several parallel flows are brought together.
What does that mean in the Petri net?
And in the Petri net, it
means that we have to merge
again such two tokens that
were created in such a situation.
And how can we do that?
Yes with a transition that has two places
in the precondition instead of in the postcondition.
So this kind of representation in the activity diagram
would correspond to such a situation in a Petri net.
A transition that consumes and
merges tokens from two separate flows.
In the sense that
it outputs only one token.
And here again it can be that these
are not necessarily for example object node places.
But simply auxiliary places, which are perhaps necessary,
because over here directly an action node in
the activity diagram stands, which corresponds
to a transition in the Petri net.
And then there is an auxiliary place that
mediates from this transition
to this merge transition.
We will also see this in the example.
That's exactly where it appears.
So in our example activity diagram it
was so that this becomes a transition.
This also becomes a transition, because that's
the way it is with actions and
join nodes
in the activity diagram.
Then there must be
an auxiliary place in between.
O.k., and as with the merge
and decision nodes, it can also be
the case with the merges
and forks that, for example,
they have both characteristics at
the same time, so to speak.
So a bar doesn't necessarily have to
have one input, multiple outputs, or vice-versa.
It could also have multiple inputs
at the top and multiple outputs at the bottom.
That would then also
be represented with a
bar like that, but often it's
actually exactly a fork or merge.
So really splitting or merging,
not a mixture of those.
O.k. of course a
certain discipline is useful.
So often it will be
the case that a merge occurs when
there were also fork nodes before.
So, in this example, it is
no coincidence that this and this
bar somehow belong together.
So this bar consumes
exactly the split flows,
which have originated here above.
Somehow a discipline that if
somewhere a splitting takes place,
afterwards also again
a merging takes place.
The activity diagrams don't specify that per
se, that it always has to be.
But in the example, that will often be the
case, that there is such a correspondence of these nodes.
O.k., and then from the
example activity diagram the special
nodes for the start and for the
end of the processing are still missing.
222 # slide
The one for the start.
That was this filled circle
that had no incoming edge.
It wasn't allowed that either.
So this start node is not allowed to have any
incoming edges, but it's allowed to have several outgoing edges.
And what corresponds to
this in a Petri net?
Well simply a place,
which is initially marked.
So a place where a token
lies at the beginning, so that
a control flow/flow can
come into being at all.
How many tokens are there?
As many as there are
outgoing edges from the start node.
So it could be that from a
start node in the activity diagram two edges go out.
For example one to the right and one
downwards, then there should be two tokens in
the translated Petri net
on this corresponding start place.
So that one can start the
flow to the right, so to speak.
So a transition can fire, which
would stand here on the right,
accordingly any action nodes,
which are located here.
If there is still a second exit
with further actions here below perhaps, then there
would have to be just
here the second token, so
that also the transitions which are
translated and drawn in here below can fire.
So a place with as many tokens
as arrows going out from the start
node of the activity diagram.
O.k., then there is such a rule that
these edges do not lead to object nodes.
So the intuition is that object nodes
are supposed to, yes hold some concrete artifacts,
like the plan earlier, and that
must always be preceded by an action.
So objects don't just come
into existence out of thin air.
The idea would be, if we want to have
an object, like in the activity diagram for building a
house, then we would have a start node.
That sort of sets an action in motion, and
then from that action, an object can come into being,
which is put on an object node.
But direct transitions
from these start nodes
to object nodes do not
exist according to activity diagrams.
What is allowed is that there are
several start nodes in an activity diagram.
Unlike in the flat state diagram, where
there was always one designated start node, in
the activity diagram there may be
several start nodes represented this way.
And that fits, because in Petri nets
we can have multiple places
at the beginning that have tokens.
And that's what would happen here.
If we have two start
nodes in the activity diagram, the
translated Petri net would also have two places, in
which at least one token lies at the beginning.
And then actions/transitions can fire at the
same time at different places at the beginning.
O.k., and then there must
be something for the end.
With a start comes an end.
In fact, there are two
different forms in the activity diagram.
Only one of them we had seen so far.
223 # slide
So in the example this element appeared.
The so-called activity end.
That's actually supposed
to, if it's reached,
by a flow, so to
speak, end the activity completely.
So all the control and object flows that are
still going on in the activity diagram, so to speak,
would be terminated immediately when one
of these activity end elements is reached.
There is no direct equivalent
for this in Petri nets.
In Petri nets, you can't describe
somewhere "when that place is reached, then
all of a sudden all tokens
in the entire Petri net disappear".
In Petri nets everything is always local.
What rather happens in Petri nets is what
corresponds to the end of flow in activity diagrams.
Namely, that eats, so to speak,
only the control flow running into it.
That would correspond to a transition
that only has incoming but no outgoing edges.
So it eats tokens running into
it and does not output anything else.
So, it eats only locally the
tokens at this place and not somehow
all tokens, which are on the way
throughout the whole Petri net.
Petri net on the way.
It always depends
on the concrete example,
if there is a difference
between these two possible ends.
So in the example what I had here,
I had used though this activity end as symbol.
I could also have taken the flow end,
because here in the example it is anyway
so that only one token is on the way.
So it is split here
times, but linked again before.
That means, if somehow a token arrives here at the
bottom, then in the whole remaining Petri net, activity diagram/Petri
net, there can't be another
token on the way somewhere.
So this is anyway the only
token which is still on the
way here and if this is eaten,
the processing as a whole is over.
In more complicated situations,
where there were more start nodes and
therefore more tokens are on the way,
it could make a difference if I
have this activity end or flow end.
But we'll be careful in tasks that you
get that that doesn't fall on your feet.
And somehow the
difference causes you problems.
So in examples that we're going to
look at, it's always uniquely
convertible how you describe the end.
Outgoing edges are not allowed from
either the activity end or the
flow end, because they're
supposed to be just positions
where a flow ends and doesn't
somehow go a little bit further.
O.k., how we implement this,
we can see directly in the example
Petri net, for the house building example.
So that was our
house building activity diagram.
And we have now actually seen
in principle for all elements occurring in
it, how they can be translated into Petri
net components, except for this somewhat spongy end.
There I had only indicated grade,
that will be as a rule somehow.
Either a place, where a token lands,
but then it doesn't go on from there.
Or a transition that eats
a token and doesn't output anything.
And actually we can do what
I had done on the intermediate slides
now for individual excerpts/individual
parts of the activity diagram.
Tinker together overall and then get
a Petri net, which describes the
same context/behavior as should be
represented by this activity diagram.
That would essentially just
be tinkering together the
components that we've seen now
for individual excerpts throughout the slides.
224 # slide
And when we do that,
it creates this Petri net.
That already has a very
similar shape to the activity diagram.
And in fact, you can
now assign here the individual components
of the activity diagram each corresponding
places and transitions in the Petri net.
Yes, this is here the beginning of
the start nodes: a place with a token.
Then we see here the individual
transitions, which correspond to the actions here.
We see, about the place we had
also motivated that we need an auxiliary
place in between because we can't go
directly from action to action/transition to transition.
So that then corresponds to that auxiliary place
and also the other parts here are all
motivated by how we wanted
to translate individual activity diagram elements.
So this became a
place, this became a place,
this became a transition with
two outgoing arrows to action nodes.
Since these are transitions, there
can't be a direct connection there.
Instead, there has to be an auxiliary
place introduced and that's what we're seeing here.
So that would correspond
to the fork node.
That corresponds to
the, these two transitions
correspond to the two actions
in these two concurrent paths.
And then in between there has
to be just an auxiliary place.
And so there's a clear
way to get from the activity
diagram that we've seen to a Petri net.
And we see also the end I have
implemented here, in which simply here the last action,
this transition, is
such a swallowing transition,
which corresponds to the fact that after
finishing the house nothing more happens.
This end of flow here, this
end of activity, I have simply implemented
by the fact that the transition, which I have
introduced for this, has no more output for this action.
This is then just shown here.
O.k., most of the places
here are really such auxiliary places.
You see here the
named elements are elements that
also appeared in the activity diagram.
Especially this place, which
corresponds to an object node.
Most of the other places are
auxiliary places introduced to make
this a legal Petri net.
There is only one auxiliary
transition in this particular case.
That is this one, which was necessary so that
I can get from this place to that place.
Which corresponded in
the activity diagram
to these two elements, where
there is nothing else in between.
But I am not allowed to go from
place to place directly in the Petri net.
O.k., and actually all that
we intuitively saw in the activity
diagram at possible step sequences, that
would be exactly all valid transition sequences,
which represent valid firing
in this Petri net.
Insofar as this Petri net
models exactly the same thing
as the activity
diagram we originally saw.
And this is a general recipe how
to get Petri nets from activity diagrams.
As long as only elements
we discussed occur, of course.
O.k., in fact there are
many more representation possibilities in activity
diagrams, and we won't
introduce all of them.
I'll touch on and mention a few now.
But for those I will not always
give a full translation in Petri nets.
Of course, in exercises or exams
you must only be able to translate
activity diagrams into Petri nets for
which we have actually discussed this.
So for the elements that occur in
it, for which I had slides here.
But what would
be some additional expressions?
225 # slide
Well, in activity diagrams in UML, on the
one hand, there are further borrowings from Petri nets,
and on the other hand, there
are simply own syntax/own representation options.
For example, at object nodes you can specify the
maximum number of objects that can be located there.
And this is of course something that
corresponds to the capacity in Petri nets.
Yes, this notation 6 here in
a Petri net with capacity also corresponds
to the information that there can
never be more than six tokens.
And this would be
represented in the activity
diagram in such a way that
one indicates an upper bound here.
O.k. so a quantitative
statement at an object node.
There are also quantitative statements at the
transitions, there can be a weight at it.
And this corresponds exactly to the
weight concept also in a Petri net.
Yes, so "upperBound" would
say here, there can
be a maximum of six dishes at
the same time here as a reservoir.
And the weight would say, there are
always two dishes served at the same time.
In the Petri net:
This place has capacity 6.
And this link/the
connection has weight two.
This did not occur
in the example considered so
far, but can be applied to
concepts from Petri nets as well.
Especially if we consider
Petri nets with capacity.
O.k., what activity diagrams allow, which
we didn't have in Petri nets.
Was that even in such situations, where
here, for example, several tokens are deposited
and then taken out one by one, yes,
you can describe in what
order that happens to the.
This makes no sense with Petri nets.
If there are six tokens
here, then I don't care which of
the six tokens will be served next.
On the other hand, in a
restaurant application, where six dishes are put
here one after the other
and are also finished, it might
be important which of these
six dishes are served next.
Namely, if possible, the ones that have been standing
the longest, so that they don't get even colder.
Yes, so you can specify an
order of objects, so to speak.
But we won't look at that any further.
You should just know that it's possible.
And I found that to know that it's
possible, but we're not going to consider that further.
Because we didn't do it at all
on the Petri net side either, and it
wouldn't make much sense there because, after all,
the individual tokens are not distinguishable at all.
Unlike concrete objects in a
concrete software modeling context, perhaps.
226 # slide
O.k. so the point here is:
This correspondence, it's
not completely exact.
Yes not for all concepts from
activity diagram there is a direct translation.
And of course it's also because
activity diagrams are
so semi-formal anyway.
So not all aspects are
fully specified in it at all.
In the same sense as
Petri nets were completely mathematically modeled.
But for large parts of activity diagrams
you can do a translation as well.
And we will only deal with those
in the tasks.
227 # slide
O.k. what else do we have?
Activity areas.
These are simply a representation, so to speak,
which does not occur in Petri nets either.
In Petri nets, there are simply
places, transitions, and connections in between.
In activity diagrams one
structures the diagrams even further,
under certain circumstances.
One groups elements.
For example, here you could imagine
if we have this restaurant example.
Then there could be
two areas of responsibility,
so to speak, or perhaps a spatial
distribution: the kitchen and the guest room.
And then, for example, there
are actions here that are
just carried out by the guest and
actions that are carried out by the waiter.
And then one can use this representation with
such a decomposition of the plane into several
areas, to which then
these elements are assigned to express these responsibilities.
So the actions that take
place here are exactly "order dish",
"take order", "serve dish", "eat dish".
This representation does not change anything,
but it makes it clearer for the
reader of this diagram, which
action is conceptually carried out by whom.
And there are several
possibilities how this can be.
It could also go back and forth.
There is also the possibility
to create object nodes on this
border, where the intuition is that
there is a transfer, so to speak.
From one area to the other.
But this does not appear
in the example here, and
it certainly does not appear
in our house construction example.
We didn't have that
kind of structuring there.
So it's more of a documentation
of who is responsible for what action.
It doesn't change the order
of firing or what firing actions
are possible, what sequences
of actions are possible.
It has little effect on the semantics,
so to speak, of the activity diagram or
the firing sequences in
a translated Petri net.
228 # slide
O.k., and then there are various other
elements that we don't even discuss
here, that I don't even show you.
You could just read
up on them from literature.
You don't have to for this lecture,
because we don't look at those things.
There are various other elements,
each with its own representation,
that did not and will
not appear in our examples.
That's just as a bullet point again,
that you realize that UML activity diagrams have
even more richness of variation
than we've already seen here.
And in any case more than Petri
nets, where there were only places and transitions.